<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<document>
 <metadata>
  <sourcename>Sacred Texts</sourcename>
  <sourceurl>http://www.sacred-texts.com/neu/vig/index.htm</sourceurl>
  <wordcount>25513</wordcount>
  <creator>SagaDB.org build mechanism</creator>
  <title_orig>Víga-Glúms saga</title_orig>
  <language>English</language>
  <chapters>28</chapters>
  <basename>viga-glums_saga.en</basename>
  <language_iso>en</language_iso>
  <trans>Edmund Head</trans>
  <editor>Sveinbjorn Thordarson</editor>
  <trans_date>1866</trans_date>
  <date_added>2007-09-13-17-10-27</date_added>
  <title>The Saga of Viga-Glum</title>
 </metadata>
 <content>
  <chapter number="1" title="">
   <paragraph>There was a man called Ingiald, who lived at Thverá, on the Eyjafirth; he was  one of the original priests and a great chief, and he was already in years  when this story begins.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Ingiald was married, and had two sons, Steinolf and Eyiolf, both right  good men and fair to see. Ingiald himself was self-willed, reserved, hard  to deal with, and obstinate. He cared little for merchants, and did not  choose to submit to their arrogance. If he wanted anything from them,  he preferred sending other people for it to going himself.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>One summer a ship came  into Eyjafirth, the master of which was named Hreidar: he was a man of  great family, who had his home at Vorz in Norway, and was very courageous  and very popular. Ingialds son, Eyiolf, was often about the ship in the  course of the summer, and he and Hreidar became great friends. Hreidar  told him he should like to pass the winter here in some house, and from  the report he had heard he should prefer that of Ingiald. Eyiolf said  that such was not his fathers wont, but still that he would see about  it. When he came home, he spoke to his father and asked him to take the  master of the ship into his house--that he was a good, worthy fellow--and  pleaded strongly in his behalf. Ingiald replied, If youhave invited  him already, what is the use of talking about it? I must bear my part  in meeting the expense, and you must bear yours in taking all the trouble;  but he added that he had never had a foreigner staying with him before  and that he was still not desirous of doing so. Then Eyiolf answered,  It has not yet been settled without your consent; but I have not had  much share in the management of the house as yet, and it seems your will  that I should not have much, if a guest is not to be received whom I have  invited hither. Well, said Ingiald, you shall have your own way in  this matter, and the master and one other man may come here. I shall make  no charge, for your sake; but you must take all the trouble for them,  and I will defray the cost. I am well pleased, replied Eyiolf, that  so it should be.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Eyiolf went the next day,  found Hreidar, and told him how matters stood, whereupon Hreidar expressed  his satisfaction and betook himself, with his cargo, to Ingialds house.  A short time afterwards he learned that there was to be a great gathering  there at Christmas. In the meantime Ingiald, though reserved, was on good  terms with him.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>One day Hreidar asked  Ingiald to go into the outhouse where his cargo was; and when he went  he invited him to choose whatever he liked out of his goods. Ingiald said  that he did not wish to take any of his property, but acknowledged his  liberality. Hreidar replied, I have, however, thought of something that  you may want from us. I have been in several of the best dwellings here  in Eyjafirth, and I have seen none so good as this; but the hangings for  your hall are not such as to surpass those of other people. So saying,  he took from his chests a set of hangings of such quality that no better  had ever come to Iceland, and gave them to Ingiald, who thanked him; and  a friendly feeling was now established between them. In the course of  the winter Eyiolf said that he should like to sail with Hreidar on his  outward voyage, but Hreidar did not answer him very readily. Why, says  Eyiolf, will you not take me with you? Do you not like me? I like you  right well, but your father will not approve of such a return for his  hospitality, and I should not like to repay his kindness by taking away  a son who is such a credit to him. If he approves, I shall willingly take  you with me, and be truly thankful for your going.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Now the traders prepared  for their voyage, and when they were ready, Eyiolf again asked Hreidar  about taking him out: he told him what he wanted, and how he did not mean  to act in this matter against his fathers wishes. Afterwards, he told  his father how anxious he was to go, and what had passed between himself  and Hreidar. Ingiald said there were few such mean as Hreidar to be found,  and what with your own conduct and his tried worth, I shall allow you  to go, for I am sure you had better make the voyage with him than with  any one else.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="2" title="">
   <paragraph>Then they sailed and arrived in Norway; and Heidar laid before Eyiolf many  schemes for disposing of himself, but he would not agree to anything which  was proposed. Well, said Hreidar, what are your plans, then? I really  do not know. Will you not visit the king, or some of the other great  men? You would, as a matter of course, be entitled to every assistance  from us. (At this time Hacon, the ward of Athelstan, ruled in Norway.)  Such chiefs are the persons whom you ought  to serve. Eyiolf answered, I am not well fitted for a kings service;  and though things might turn out as I should desire, yet I decline the  proposal. Hreidar said, What will you do, then? Why, replied Eyiolf,   do you shirk asking me to your own house? for that is what I want.  I do not like to offer you that which it is not good you should accept,  and good alone ought you to have at my hands. I am curious, said Eyiolf,  to know how this matter stands. You shall know all about it, answered  Hreidar, although it befits me ill to speak of it. I have a brother named  Ivar; we live together, and hold our property jointly, and are very fond  of one another; but we are not of the same mind in one thing, for he cannot  bear any Icelander; so that they are not safe where he is. He is out sea-roving  all the summer; but when he comes home, he takes up his quarters in my  house, with ten or twelve men, and everybody there has to look to their  wishes. All these fellows will be so ill-disposed towards you, that you  would not in any way be comfortable there.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>I am very curious, said  Eyiolf, to learn what these men are like, and whatever happens, it will  be no fault of yours, if you let the visit take place. Hreidar replied,  I owe this to my brother, seeing that he brings me home the excellent  gifts which he does--not to let a difference arise between us on your  account--and I shall be very much vexed if they mock and insult you.  Ah! you want terribly to get out of having me at your house, remarked  Eyiolf; but how will he bear himself towards me--will he beat me? It  will be something worse than beating; he has many ill-conditioned men  with him, and they will put the worst construction on all you do or say.  Eyiolf said, Thats no great trial. If a man knows it before, it is folly  not to bear that sort of thing: that shall be no hindrance. Hreidar replied,  There is a difficulty both ways--you are my friend, and he is my brother,  whom I love much.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>The end of it was that  Eyiolf went to stay at Hreidars, on the promontory; and when Ivar was  expected home, he put on a great fur cloak, which he wore every day; he  was a tall man, and sat always at Hreidars side.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="3" title="">
   <paragraph>Now, when Ivar arrived, they went out to meet him as a mark of honour, and  received him joyfully. Either brother then aksed the other for tidings  and Ivar inquired of Hreidar where he had been through the winter. Hreidar  told him he had been in Iceland, and then Ivar asked no more about the  matter; but tell me, said he, is that great rough lump I see there  a man, or is it some animal? Eyiolf answered, I am a man of Iceland,  my name is Eyiolf, and I intend to be here all the winter. I guess one  thing, said Ivar; we shall not be without mischief of some kind, if  an Icelander is here. Hreidar replied, If you deal badly with him, so  that he cannot stay here, the affection between us, as near kinsmen, will  suffer. It was a bad voyage of yours to Iceland, said Ivar, if we  on that account are to be dependent on Icelanders, or cast off our own  friends and kindred: nor do I know why you chose to visit that most hateful  people; and then too you have escaped telling me what has happened to  you. It is very different  from what you suppose, said Hreidar; there are many good fellows there.  Well, replied Ivar, at any rate that rough and shaggy beast does not  look particularly well on the high seat. But when he saw that his brother  set great store by Eyiolf he did not speak so strongly as before against  Icelanders. What can I call him, said he, except Lump? and Eyiolf  did not seem to object to the name; but they made the worst of everything  that he did.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>There was a man named  Vigfuss, lord of the district of Vorz, the son of Sigurd, who was the  son of Kari-Viking; and Vigfuss had a daughter, called Astrida. Hreidar  and Ivar were great friends of Vigfuss, and they used to entertain one  another alternate winters, at Christmas. At this time it was the turn  of the brothers to prepare for the feast. In fact Hreidar had got everything  ready, and had then to invite his guest. He asked Eyiolf to go with him,  for, said he, I have no curiosity to try how they will behave towards  you here. I am not well, replied Eyiolf, and I cannot go. That evening,  when Hreidar was gone and they took their places, Ivars companions exclaimed,  Now we shall amuse ourselves as we please, for old Lump is left at  home. Nay, said Ivar, we must think of something which befits us. Here  we are, two brothers, holding our property jointly, and he has all the  trouble of it, whilst I have none. This is a man to whom he wishes to  be kind, and we act in such a way that he can scarcely stay here, but  at the same time we have no fault to find with him. No man shall say anything  injurious to him whilst Hreidar is absent. They replied it was just the  time to have some sport. No, said Ivar, there is little true manhood  in what you say. Every one waits on us here, and we have all the sport  we choose, but others have the labour and care. If that man had killed  my brother, I would not, for Hreidars sake, do him any harm, and no one  shall dare to make sport of him. He shall not be called Lump any longer.  In the morning Ivar spoke with Eyiolf: Will you go into the wood with  us and amuse yourself He assented to this and went with them: they took  to cutting down trees and carrying them home. Eyiolf had with him his  sword and a hatchet. I advise you, Icelander, said Ivar, if our men  go each his on way, that you get home before dark. So each man went his  own way, and Eyiolf went off by himself, and taking off his rough cloak,  laid upon it the sword which he hand in his hand. Then he turned into  the wood to amuse himself with his hatchet, and cut down the trees which  he fancied. As the day advanced it came on to snow, and he thought of  going home; but when he came to the spot where he had left his cloak it  was gone, and the sword remained behind. He saw a track in the snow as  if the cloak had been dragged along. A bear had come and carried off the  cloak, but had hardly had strength to hold it off the ground, for it was  a young bear, just come out of its lair, that had never killed a man.  They Eyiolf went and saw the bear sitting before him, so he drew his sword  and cut off its snout close to the eyes and took it home with him in his  hand. Ivar came home first, missed Eyiolf, and exclaimed, We have made  a bad expedition of it, and we have done wrong in parting from our comrade  in the wood, for he does not know his way in it. It is likely that there  are wild beasts there, and considering the footing on which we have been  with him, it would be much talked about, if he did not get safe back.  I advise that we should go and look for him till we find him. When they  got out before the door, there was Eyiolf coming to meet them, and Ivar  greeted him well, and asked how he came to be covered with blood. Eyiolf  showed them what he held in his hand, and Ivar said, I fear you are wounded?  but he answered, Dont trouble yourself about me; I have no hurt. Ivar  exclaimed, What folly it is to mock men whom we do not know! He has shown  in this matter a courage which I doubt if any of us would come up to.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>The following evening  Hreidar came home, and Ivar asked him, Why are you so moody, brother?  Are you anxious about Lump? How do you think I am likely to have dealt  with him? No doubt, said Hreidar, it is of some consequence how you  have acted in this matter. What will you give me, if I should be on  the same terms with him as you are yourself? I will give you, answered  Hreidar, that gold ring which belongs to both of us and which you have  long liked. Ivar replied, I dont covet your property, but I shall for  the future stand to him in the same relation as to yourself, and henceforth  he shall sit by my side, and not by yours. Then both of them held Eyiolf  in high honour, and felt that the place he sat in was worthily filled;  and so it went on.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="4" title="">
   <paragraph>Now people came to the Christmas  feast, and those who were to sit together were told off in messes of twelve.  Lots were cast to see who should sit next to Astrida, the daughter of  the chief Vigfuss, and Eyiolf always drew the lot for sitting by her side.  No one observed that they talked together more than other persons did,  but still men said that it was fated to come about in that way that he  should marry her. The feast came to an end, after being celebrated with  great splendour, and the guest were dismissed with presents. Eyiolf went  sea-roving for four summers, and was held to be a very valiant man. He  gained great reputation and much booty. It happened one winter that a  certain Thorstein came to Vorz, who was a great friend of the brothers,  and lived in the upland country. He told them of the strait he was in;  how the Berserker, who  was called Asgaut, had challenged him to the holmgang, because he had  refused to give him his sister, and he asked them to escort him to the  field with a large number of men, so that the pirate might not seize on  his property. He added that Asgaut had killed many of his people, and  that he must give up his sister to him if they would not support him;  for, said he, I have no confidence in the result of the holmgang,  unless I have the benefit of the good luck which attends you.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>They did not like to refuse  to go with him, and so they went into the upland with thirty men in their  company; when they got to the place of meeting the question was put to  all the people there, Was there any man who desired to win a wife by  fighting Asgaut? but though the lady was attractive enough, there was  no one ready to win her a that price. Then the brothers asked Eyiolf to  bear Thorsteins shield for him in the fight, but he replied that he never defended any other man, and not even himself  in that way. I shall not like it, said he, if he is killed whilst he  is under my care, and there could be no honour in that. But if this  young fellow is slain on our hands now, what are we to do? Are we to go  away again when that is done, or are we to get a second and third man  to fight the Berserker? Our disgrace will only increase in proportion  as more men are killed on our side, and we shall get little credit by  our journey if we go back without avenging him who thus falls, as it were,  on our behalf. Ask me, if you like, to fight the Berserker myself; that  is a thing one may do for ones friends, but what you now ask I will not  grant. They thanked him much, but the stake to be risked seemed very  great in his case.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Well, observed Eyiolf,  my opinion is, that none of our people ought to go back to their homes  again, if the man who falls is not avenged, and I think it worse to fight  the Berserker after your kinsman is killed than it would be before. So  he stepped forward, and Ivar offered to hold the shield for him. Eyiolf  answered-- It is well offered, but the matter concerns me most, and the  old proverb is true, a mans own hand is most to be trusted. Then he  went on to the holm, and the Berserker called out, Is that fellow going  to fight with me? Is it not true, said Eyiolf, that you are afraid  to fight with me? It may be that you are not of the right sort when you  fear a big man, and crow over a little one. That has never been laid  to my charge, replied the Berserker, but I will explain to you the laws  of the combat. If I am wounded I am to get off by paying five marks.  Oh, said Eyiolf, I do not feel bound to keep any rules with you, when  you set your own price on yourself, and that price is one which in our  country would be paid for a thrall. Eyiolf had to strike the first blow,  and that first blow he struck in such a way that if fell on the point  of the Berserkers shield, and cut it off, and his foot along with it.  He got great honour by this feat, and returned home with the brothers.  A good deal of money was offered for his acceptance, but he said he had  not done the deed for the sake of money, nor for the sake of the lady,  but out of friendship for Hreidar and Ivar. Asgaut paid the fine to be  released from the duel, and lived a maimed man.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>After all this Eyiolf  wooed Astrida, the daughter of Vigfuss, and the brothers went to press  his suit for him. They said he was a man of great family, who held a good  position in Iceland, and had many kinsmen to back him, and they thought  it probable his career would be a distinguished one. Eyiolf himself then  said, It may be that Astridas friends think we are boasting in what  we say, but many know the fact of my having in Iceland an honourable descent  and a good property. Vigfuss answered, This will be her destiny, though  we did not look lower for our kinswoman, and so she was betrothed to  him and they sailed out to Iceland together.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="5" title="">
   <paragraph>There was a man named Bödvar; he was the son of Vikingakari, and the brother of  Sigurd the father of Vigfuss, whose daughter was Astrida, the mother of  Erik father of another Astrida, the mother of Olaf, the son of Tryggvi.  Vikingakari was the son of Eymund the pirate,   the son of Thorir. Bödvar was the father of Oluf the mother of Gizor the  white. When Eyiolf and his wife Astrida got out to Iceland, Ingiald was  dead, and Eyiolf succeeded to his property and his office as priest. Ingiald  had a daughter named Ulfeida, who was married to Narvi of Hrisey. Four  children of Eyiolf and Astrida are mentioned, of whom Thorstein was the  eldest, but his share of the inheritance was paid him when he married,  and he dwelt on Eyjafirth as long as he lived, and has little to do with  our story. The second was Vigfuss, who married Halfrida, the daughter  of Thorkel the tall from Myvain. Glum was the youngest of their sons,  and the daughter was named Helga. She was wedded to Steingrim of Sigluvik,  and their son was Thorvald Tafalld, who comes up afterwards in this story.  Vigfuss, however, died very soon after his marriage, leaving one child,  who survived him a short time only, and thus it came to pass that all  his property vested half in Halfrida and half in Glum and Astrida, for  Eyiolf was dead before this happened. Then Thorkel the tall moved his  establishment to Thverà, and Sigmund his son with him. The latter was  a man of much importance, an looked forward to becoming chief of the district,  if he made a good match, and got the support of good kinsmen.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Thorir was the name of  a man who lived at Espihole, the son of Hamund of the dark-skin, and  of Ingunna, the daughter of Helgi the thin. He had married Thordis, the  daughter of Kadal, and their children were Thorarin and Thorvald the crooked,  who lived at Grund on the Eyjafirth, Thorgrim, who lived at Mödrufell,  Ingunna, the wife of Thord the priest of Frey, and Vigdis, who married  Sigmund.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Now Thorkel and Sigmund took to disturbing the property of Astrida, and they divided the land in half, but Glum and his mother got that part  which had no house on it. So they made their dwelling at Borgarhole, but  Glum took very little trouble about household matters, and seemed to be  somewhat slow in coming to his full faculties. He was for the most part  silent and undemonstrative, tall, of a dark complexion, with straight white hair; a powerful man, who seemed rather awkward and shy, and never went to the places where men met together.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>The temple of Frey was  on the south of the river at Hripkelstad. Thorarin, of Espihole, was a  prudent and popular man, but his brother Thorvald the crooked was a bully  and hard to deal with. Sigmund thought he should be a great man if he  could ally himself to the people at Espihole. In the meantime the property  of Glum and Astrida was getting less every day, and their condition became  uncomfortable, for Sigmund and Thorkel thwarted them, so that in everything  they got less than their share. Then Glum says to his mother that he will  go abroad, for I see clearly I shall never get on here, but it may be  I shall meet with more luck by means of the reputation of my kindred:  I do not like to bear the encroachments of Sigmund, for whom as yet I  am no match. However, do not you let go your hold on the land, through  your position may be a difficult one. Glum at that time, when he desired  to go abroad, was fifteen years of age.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="6" title="">
   <paragraph>Now we have to tell of Glums voyage. As soon as he landed in Norway he went  up to Vigfusss house; and when he came thither he saw a great crowd of  people, and all sorts of amusements and games going on. He understood  at once that everything there must be on a great scale, but he saw many  men of mark, and did not know which was his kinsman Vigfuss. He made him  out by observing a tall and distinguished-looking man, in a full blue  cloak, on the high seat, playing with a gold-mounted spear. Then Glum  went up to him and greeted him, and his greeting was received courteously.  Vigfuss asked who he was; he replied that he was an Icelander from Eyjafirth.  Vigfuss inquired after his son-in-law, and his daughter Astrida. Glum  told him that the former was dead, but that the latter was still living.  Then he asked what children of theirs were alive, and Glum gave an account  of his brothers and his sister, and added that he who now stood before  him was one of the sons, but when he had said that, the conversation went  no further. Glum asked Vigfuss to assign him a seat, but he said he did  not know how much of what had been told him was true, told him to take  a seat on the outside of the lower bench, and took little notice of him.  Glum spoke little, and was unsociable in his habits, and when men were  drinking or amusing themselves in other ways, he used to lie with his  cloak wrapt round his head, so that he seemed a sort of fool. At the commencement of winter there was a feast prepared, and a sacrifice to the gods, in which observance all were expected to take part, but Glum sat in his place  and did not attend it. As evening passed on, and the guests had arrived,  there was not so much merriment, on account of the meeting of friends  and the welcoming one another, as might have been expected when so many  had come together. On the day on which the people came, Glum had not stirred  out to meet them, nor did he ask any one to sit by him ort to take his  place.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>After they were set down  to table, it was said that the man called Biörn with the Iron Skull,  and eleven others with him, were come into the homestead. He was a great  Berserker, who used to go about to feasts where many people were assembled,  and picked a quarrel with any one who chose to say anything which he could  take hold of; the he challenged them to the holmgang: and Vigfuss therefore  desired that every one should take care what he said. For, said he,  it is less disgrace to do that than to get something worse at his hands.  This all men promised to observe, and Biörn walked into the hall and looked  for compliments, and asked the last man on the upper bench whether he  thought himself as good a man as he (Biörn) was? to which the reply was  Very far from it. Then he asked the same question of one man after the  other, until he got up in front of the high seat. People used different  words in answering him, but the end of it was that no one professed to  be his match. When he came up to Vigfuss he asked him if he knew where  to find such champions as he (Biörn) was? Vigfuss said he did not know  any men equal to him. Well, said Biörn, that is a proper and discreet  answer, as might have been expected from you, for you are an honourable  man, and your life has been according to your wishes, without any check  to your prosperity or any stain on your reputation. It is well therefore  that I need address nothing but fair words to you, but I wish to ask you  one question--Do you think yourself as good a man as I am? Vigfuss replied,  When I was young, out sea-roving and getting some honour of my own--well,  I do not know whether I might then have been your match, but now I am  not half as good, for I am old and decrepid. Biörn turned away and proceeded  further out along the second bench, and went on asking men whether they  were his equals, but they all answered that they were not so. At last  he came to the place where Glum lay stretched out on the bench. Why does  this fellow lie there, said Biörn, and not sit up? Glums comrades  answered for him and spoke on his behalf, and said that he was so dull  that it mattered little what he said. Biörn gave him a kick, told him  to sit up like other people, and asked him if he was as brave a man as  he? Glum replied that Biörn had no need to meddle with him, and that he  (Glum) knew nothing about his courage; but there is one reason, he added,  why I should not like to be put on the same footing with you, and that  is because out there, in Iceland, a man would be called a fool who conducted  himself as you do, but here I see everybody regulates his speech in the  most perfect manner. Then he jumps up, pulls Biörns helmet off, catches  up a stick of firewood, and brings it down between his shoulders, so that  the great champion bends beneath the stroke. Glum gives him one blow after  another till he is down, and then, as he tries to get on his feet, he  smites him on the head, and so he goes on till he gets him outside the  door. When Glum wanted to return to his seat, Vigfuss had come down from  the dais to the floor of the hall and greeted his kinsman, telling him  that he had now shown what he was, and proved that he belonged to the  race. Now I shall honour you as befits us, said Vigfuss; and he added  that he acted as he had done at first, because Glum seemed slow and stupid.  I chose to wait till you on your way into our family by some act of manhood.  Then he led him up to a seat next himself, and Glum told him he would  have accepted that place before, if it had been offered to him. The next  day they heard of Biörns death, and Vigfuss offered Glum to succeed to  himself in his position and dignity. The latter said he would accept the  offer, but he must first go to Iceland in order to see that his inheritance  there did not fall into the hands of those whom he did not choose should  enjoy it, but that he would return as soon as possible. Vigfuss expressed  his conviction that Glum would do credit to his race and increase his  reputation in Iceland. So when summer came he got a ship ready for Glum,  and put a cargo on board, with much store of gold and silver, and said  to him, I feel sure we shall not see one another again; but certain special  gifts I will give you, that is to say, a cloak, a spear, and a sword,  which we in this family have put great trust in. Whilst you retain these  articles, I expect that you will never lose your honour; but if you part  with them, then I have my fears: and so they separated.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="7" title="">
   <paragraph>Glum sailed out to Iceland, and went home to Thverá, where he straightway found his mother. She received him gladly, and told him the unfairness of Sigmund and his father towards her. She bade him however have patience, for that  she was not able to cope with them. Then he rode to the homestead, and  saw that the fence ran in such a way as to encroach on his property, and  he sung these verses:--</paragraph>
   <poetry>
    <line>Yes! closer than I thought, fair dame,</line>
    <line>This hedge so green hath hemmd us in;</line>
    <line>Our peace at home is spoilt, and shame</line>
    <line>Must cling to us and all our kin.</line>
    <line>I sing it now, but in the fray</line>
    <line>I soon shall have to draw my sword.</line>
    <line>Too surely, whilst Ive been away,</line>
    <line>My land hath found a wrongful lord.</line>
   </poetry>
   <paragraph>What had occurred whilst he was absent, was that Sigmund had worried Astrida,  and evidently wanted to drive her off her land. In the autumn, before  Glum returned, Sigmund and Thorkel had lost two heifers, and supposed  they had been stolen. Their suspicions fell on the serfs of Astrida, who,  they said, had no doubt killed and eaten them off hand, and they caused  these serfs to be summoned in the spring for the theft. Now these were  the best men Astrida had, and she thought she could hardly mange her farm  if they went away. So she went to her son Thorstein, and told him what  wrong Sigmund and his father were doing her, and asked him to answer for  her serfs. I would rather atone for them in money, she said, than that  they should be found guilty on a false charge, and I should think it your  business now to stand before us, and to show yourself worthy of a good  name. Thorstein seemed to think that the prosecutors would so follow  up the matter as to bring the full force of their family interest to bear  on it. And if, said he, these serfs are essential to your household,  we had better take such a share of the fine as will make it possible to  get the money to pay it. Yes, she answered, but I hear that the only  atonement they will take is one which is intended to ruin us. However,  as I see there is a little help to be got where you are, the matter must  rest in their hands.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>One of the best things  about the estate at Thverá was a certain field known by the name of the  Suregiver, which was never without a crop. It had been so arranged in  the partition of the land that either party should have this field year  and year about. Then Astrida said to Thorkel and Sigmund, It is clear  thay you wish to push me hard, and you see that I have no one to manage  for me, but rather than give up my serfs I will leave the affair to be  settled on your own terms. They replied that was very prudent on her  part, and after consulting together they decided that they must either  declare the men guilty, or award what damages they thought proper. But  Thorstein did not stir in the case, so as to take the award out of their  hands, and they assigned to the field to themselves, as sole owners, with  the intention of getting hold of all her land, by thus depriving her of  the main prop of her housekeeping. And that very summer which was coming  on, she ought, if she had her rights, to have had the field.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Now, in the summer, when  men were gone to the Thing, and when this suit had been thus settled,  the herdsmen going round the pastures found the two heifers in a landslip,  where the snow had drifted over them early in the winter, and thus the  calumny against Astridas serfs was exposed. When Thorkel and Sigmund  heard that the heifers had bee found, they offered money to pay for the  field, but they refused to renounce the conveyance which had been made  of it to them. Astrida however answered that it would not be too great  a compensation for the false charge which had been go up, if she were  allowed to have what was her own. So, said she, I will either have  what belongs to me, or I will submit to the loss; and though there is  no one here to set the matter straight, I will wait, and I expect that  Glum will come out and put it in the right way. Sigmund replied, It  will be a long time before he ploughs for that harvest. Why, there is  that son of yours, who is a much fitter man to help you, sitting by and  doing nothing. Pride and wrong, said she, often end badly, and this  may happen in your case.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>It was somewhat late in  the summer when Glum came out; he stayed a little while with the ship,  and then went home with his goods. His temper and character were the same  as thy had been. He gave little sign of what he thought, and seemed as  if he did not hear what had happened whilst he was away. He slept every  day till nine oclock, and took no thought about the management of the  farm. If they had had their right, the field would, as had been said,  have been that summer in the hands of Glum and his mother. Sigmunds cattle  moreover did them much injury, and were to be found every morning in their  home-field.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>One morning Astrida waked  Glum up, and told him that many of Sigmunds cattle had got into their  home-field, and wanted to break in among the hay which was laid in heaps,  and I am not active enough to drive them out, and the men are all at  work. He answered, Well, you have not often asked me to work, and there  shall be no offence in your doing so now. So he jumped up, took his horse,  and a large stick in his hand, drove the cattle briskly off the farm,  thrashing them well till they came to the homestead of Thorkel and Sigmund,  and then he let them do what mischief they please. Thorkel was looking  after the hay and the fences that morning, and Sigmund was with the labourers.  The former called out to Glum, You may be sure people will not stand  this at your hands--that you should damage their beasts in this way, though  you may have got some credit while you were abroad. Glum answered, The  beasts are not injured yet, but if they come again and trespass upon us  some of them will be lamed, and you will have to make the best of it;  it is all you will get; we are not going to suffer damage by your cattle  any longer. Sigmund cried, out, You talk big, Glum, but in our eyes  you are now just as great a simpleton as when you went away, and we shall  not regulate our affairs according to your nonsense. Glum went home,  and then a fit of laughter came upon him, and affected him in such a manner  that he turned quite pale, and tears burst from his eyes, just like large  hailstones. He was often afterwards taken in this way when the appetite  for killing some one came upon him.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="8" title="">
   <paragraph>We are told that as the autumn went on Astrida came and spoke to Glum another  morning, and, waking him up, asked him to give directions about the work,  for the haymaking, she said, would be finished this day if all was ordered  as it ought to be. Sigmund and Thorkel had already finished their hay,  and they had gone early in the morning to the field Sure-giver; and  they are no doubt very well pleased in having that field, which we should  have, if all were as it should be. Then Glum got up, but he was not ready  before nine oclock. He took his blue cloak, and his spear with gold about  it in his hand, and got his horse saddled. But Astrida said to him, You  take a good deal of pains about your dress, my son, for haymaking. His  answer was, I do not often go out to labour, but I shall do a good stroke  of work, and I will be well dressed for it. However, I am not able to  give directions for the farm-work, and I shall ride up to Hole and accept  the invitation of my brother Thorstein. So he crossed over to the south  side of the river, and as he came to the field he took the brooch out  of his cloak. Vigdis and her husband Sigmund were in the field, and when  she saw Glum she came towards him and greeted him, saying, We are sorry  that our intercourse as relations is so little, and we wish in everything  to do our part to increase it. Glum told her, I have turned in here  because the brooch is gone from my cloak, and I want you to put a stitch  in it for me. She said she would do it with pleasure, and did it accordingly.  Glum looked over the field and remarked, Sure-giver has not yet lost  his character. Then he put on his cloak again, took his spear in his  hand, and turned sharp on Sigmund, with it uplifted. Sigmund sprang up  to meet him, but Glum struck him on the head so that he needed no second  blow. Then he went up  to Vigdis, and told her to go home, and tell Thorkel, on Glums part,  nothing is yet done which will necessarily hinder our being on the footing  of kinsmen, but that Sigmund is unable to leave the field. Glum rode  on to Hole, and said nothing to his brother of what had happened; but  when Thorstein saw how he was equipped, and how he had his cloak and spear,  and perceived the blood in the ornaments of the weapon,  he asked him if he had used it within a short time. Oh, cried Glum, it is quite true; I forgot to mention it, I killed Sigmund, Thorkels son, with it to-day. That will be some  news, replied Thorstein, for Thorkel and his kinsmen at Espihole. Yes,  said glum; however, as the old saying is, The nights of blood are the  nights of most impatience. No doubt they will think less of it as time  goes on. He staid three nights at his brothers house, and then got ready  to return home. Thorstein was preparing to ride with him, but Glum told  him, Look after your won household--I shall ride the straight path home  to Thverá; they will not be so very keen in this business. So he went  home to Thverá.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Thorkel went to see Thorarin,  and asked him for counsel as to the course to be taken. His answer was,  It may now be that Astrida will say, Glum has not got on his legs for  nothing. Yes, said Thorkel, but I trow that he has got on that leg  which will not bear him long. Thorarin replied, That is as it may be.  You have long dealt unfairly with them, and tried to turn them out, without  considering what was to be expected from the descendants of one such as  Eyiolf, a man of great family and withal himself of great courage. We  are closely connected with Glum by kindred, and with you by marriage,  and the suit seems a difficult one, if Glum follows it up, as I think  he will. Thorkel then returned home, and the whole matter was kept quiet  through the winter; but Glum had somewhat more men about him than he usually  had.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="9" title="">
   <paragraph>It is said that Glum had a dream one night, in which he seemed to be standing  out in front of his dwelling, looking towards the firth; and he thought  he saw the form of a woman stalking up straight through the district from  the sea towards Thverá. She was of such height and size that her shoulders  touched the mountains on each side, and he seemed to go out of the homestead  to meet her and asked her to come to his house; and then he woke up. This  appeared very strange to every one, but he said, The dream is no doubt  a very remarkable one, and I interpret it thus--My grandfather, Vigfuss,  must be dead, and that woman who was taller than the mountains, must be  his guardian spirit, for he too was far beyond other men in honour and  in most things, and his spirit must have been looking for a place of rest  where I am. But in the summer, when the ships arrived, the news of Vigfusss  death became known, and then Glum sang as follows--</paragraph>
   <poetry>
    <line>At dead of night, beneath the sky,</line>
    <line>Upon the banks of Eyjafirth,</line>
    <line>I saw the spirit stalking by,</line>
    <line>In giant stature over the earth.</line>
   </poetry>
   <poetry>
    <line>The goddess of the sword and spear</line>
    <line>Stood, in my dream, upon this ground;</line>
    <line>And whilst the valley shook with fear,</line>
    <line>She towerd above the mountains round.</line>
   </poetry>
   <paragraph>In the spring Thorkel met Thorvald the crooked, and other sons of Thorir,  and asked them to follow up this suit of his, referring to the tie which  united them throurgh Thorirs daughter, and to all the friendship which  he and his son Sigmund had shown to them. Thorvald spoke to Thorarin,  and said that it would be discreditable to them not to help their brother-in-law, and he replied that he was ready to do all he could, and besides, he said,  It is now clear that Glum means to turn the slaying of Sigmund to account,  so as to make himself a great man, and we think ourselves worth as much  as he is in the district. Yes, replied Thorarin, but it seems to me  it will be hard to follow up the suit, so as to make sure that we shall  get any advantage by it, and on the other hand it is not unexpected that  Glum should take after his race and kindred. I am slower to move in it  than you are, because I doubt if any honour is to be got in a quarrel  with Glum; yet I should not like to see our credit lowered. Hoever, after  a certain pressure, Thorarin, the son of Thorir, set on foot at the Althing  the suit against Glum for the slaying of Sigmund; and Glum set on foot  a suit against Thorkel the tall, for slander against Astridas serfs;  and another against Sigmund, whom he charged with theft, and whom he alleged  that he had killed while trespassing on his own property. So he summoned  him as outlawed, inasmuch as he fell on his, Glums, land, and he dug  his body up. In this condition matters were when they went to the Althing.  Then Glum visited his kinsmen, and sought for help at the hands of Gizor  the white, and Teit, the son of Ketilbiörn of Mosfell, and Asgrim, the  son of Ellidagrim; and he told them the whole course of the proceedings,  and how Thorkel and Sigmund had encroached on his rights, and all the  wrong and disgrace they had inflicted on him. But from them, he said,  he expected help to put matters in a better condition. He himself would  conduct the suit. They all professed themselves bound to take care that  his cause was not left in unfriendly hands, and said they should be glad  to see him distinguish himself among their kin.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>The Thing went on till  the court sat, and the men of Espihole preferred their suit for the slaying  of Sigmund, rather as if they were egged on by those who had wrongs to  revenge, than by those who felt sure that there were no flaws in their  case. Glum too moved in the case against Thorkel, and the two suits came  before the court. Glum had many kinsmen and friends to back him, and when,  as defendant, he was called on to answer, he said, The matter is on this  wise. Every one may see that you have gone into this suit more as a question  of temper than because there were no defects in your case, for I slew  Sigmund trespassing on my own property, and before I rode to the Thing  I proclaimed him as an outlaw. Then he named his witnesses on this point,  and defended his suit with the help of his kinsmen, in such sort that  judgment was given to the effect that Sigmund had been killed out of the  pale of the law. Glum next took up the charge against Thorkel for trespass  on his property, and the case looked ill for Thorkel, for the witnesses  were on Glums side, and there was no legal defence, so that it ended  in seeking to compound the matter with the plaintiff. Glum said two courses  were open--either he would follow the case out to its conclusion, or Thorkel  must reconvey the land that Thverá at such a price as he should put on  it, which was not more than half its worth. And Thorkel may be sure,  he added, if he is convicted, that we shall not both of us be at the  Thing next summer. The friends of Thorkel now interfered to get him to  compound the suit, and he took the course which was expedient, settled  the matter, and conveyed the land to Glum. He was to live on the land  for the year, and thus, so to speak, they were on terms again. But the  men of Espihole were ill pleased with the conclusion of these suits, and  from that time they were never on a good footing with Glum. Indeed, before  Thorkel left Thverá, he went to Freys temple, and taking an old steer  up thither, made this speech:--Thou, Frey, said he, wert long my protector,  and many offerings hast thou had at my hands, which have borne good fruit  to me. Now do I present this steer to thee, in the hope that Glum hereafter  may be driven by force off this land, as I am driven off it; and, I pray  thee, give me some token whether thou acceptest this offering or not.  Then the steer was stricken in such a way that he bellowed loud and fell  down dead, and Thorkel took this a a favourable omen. Afterwards he was  in better spirits, as if he thought his offering was accepted and his  wish ratified by the god. Then he removed to Myvatn, and we have doe with  him in this story.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="10" title="">
   <paragraph>Glum now  assumed a high position in the district. There was a man named Gunnstein,  who lived at Lón in Högardal, a great and rich man, reckoned to be one  of the most important persons in the land. He had a wife called Hlif,  and their son was Thorgrim, generally known as Thorgrim the son of Hlif,  being called after his mother because she outlived his father. She was  a woman of a high spirit, and Thorgrim himself was all that a man ought  to be, and became eminent. Another son of theirs was Grim, surnamed Eyrarleggr,  and their daughter was Halldora, who was a beautiful woman of a gentle  temper. She was esteemed to be about the best match in the country both  on account of her kindred and of her own accomplishments and great qualities.  Glum paid his addresses to her, stating that he did not want the help  of kinsmen to explain what his family or his property and personal merits  were. All that you know well enough, and I have set my mind on this marriage  is so be that it is agreeable to her friends. He received a favourable  answer to his suit, and Halldora was betrothed to him with a great portion;  so the wedding went of prosperously, and Glums position became one of  more dignity that it was before.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Thorvald was the son of  Reim, who lived at Bard, in the Fleets:   he had to wife Thurida, the daughter of Thord of Höfdi. Their children  were Klaufi and Thorgerda, whom Thorarin of Espihole had married. Thorvald  the crooked of Grund wedded Thorkatla of Thiorsádal. Hlenni the Old, the  son of Ornolf Wallet-back, dwelt at Vidines, and he had to wife Otkatla,  the daughter of Otkel of Thiorsádal. Gizor was the son of Kadal, and lived  at The Tarns, in the valley of Eyjafirth; his wife was named Saldis,  and she was a worthy matron. Gizor was one of the most considerable landowners,  well to do in respect of property, with two daughters, named Thordis and  Herpruda, both handsome women, who were distinguished in dress and appearance  and were considered good matches. They grew up to womanhood at home. Gizors  brother was called Runolf, and he was the father of Valgerda, mother of  Eyiolf of Mödrufell. Thordis was Kadals daughter, and she was married  to Thorir of Espihole, and they had the children who have been named before.  Thorgrim, however, the son of Thorir, although born in wedlock, was not  the child of Thordis. He was a brave and well conditioned man, and he  set out to meet Gizor and ask Thordis his daughter to wife for himself.  His brothers and kinsmen too were engaged in pressing this suit. The maidens  relatives thought that they ought all to have a voice in the disposal  of their kinswoman, and they all considered the proposal an excellent  one; but notwithstanding this Thorgrim was refused. It seemed to pepole  in general that Thorgrim had proposed a fair and equal match, and his  brothers and kinsmen were offended at his rejection.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="11" title="">
   <paragraph>We must  now bring into the story the man named Arnor, who was called Red-cheek,  the son of Steinolf, the son of Ingiald and first cousin of Glum. He had  been long abroad, but was highly esteemed, and constantly with Glum when  he was in Iceland. He suggested to Glum to get him a wife. Glum asked  him what woman he wished to woo? He replied, Thordis, the daughter of  Gizor, who was refused to Thorgrim, the son of Thorir. Well, said Glum,  that seems to me a hopeless proposal, for there is nothing to choose  betwixt you two personally; but Thorgrim has a good establishment, plenty  of money, and many kinsmen to back him, whereas you, on the other hand,  have no household and not much property. I do not want to offer an unequal  match to Gizor, so as to prevent him doing the best for his daughter,  as he wishes, for Gizor deserves well at my hands. Arnor answered him,  I get the benefit of having good friends, if I make a better match in  consequence of your urging my suit. Promise him your friendship, and then  he will give me the girl. Indeed, it might have been called a fair match  enough, if she had not been already refused to so good a man as Thorgrim.  Glum allowed himself to be persuaded and went with Arnor to Gizor and  pressed the matter on his behalf. Gizors answer was, It may be, Glum,  that people will say I have made a mistake, if I give to Arnor, your kinsman,  my daughter, whom I did not choose to give to Thorgrim. Well, said  Glum, there is some reason in that; but it may also be said, if you will  give proper weight to what I say, that my hearty friendship is to be thrown  into the balance. Gizor replied, Yes; but, on the other side, I suspect  there will be the emnity of other people. Well, said Glum, you see  your way before you; but I tell you that what you do makes a great difference  in my disposition towards you. Then said Gizor, You shall not go away  this time without succeeding; so he gave him his and, and the girl was  betrothed to Arnor. Glum insisted on one condition--that the bridal was  to be at Thverá in the autumn; and they parted on this understanding.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Now Arnor had some malt  out at Gásar, and he himself and one of his men were to fetch it.  Thorgrim, son of Thorir, went to the  warm spring on the very day on which they were expected in with the malt,  and he was at the bath at Hrafnagil with six of his own men in his company.  So when Arnor was coming up and wanted to cross the river, Thorgrim exclaimed,  Is not this a lucky hit, now, to stumble on Arnor? Do not let us miss  the malt, at any rate, if we have missed the lady. They went at them  with their swords uplifted, and Arnor, when he saw what the difference  in their number was, jumped right into the river and got across; but his  pack-horses remained on the west side of the stream. Ah! exclaimed Thorgrim,  we are not altogether out of luck; we shall drink the ale, if they get  the wife. So he rode off to South Espihole. Thorir was then quite blind,  and Thorgrims companions were very merry and laughed aloud. Then Thorir  asked what seemed so laughable to them. They said they did not know which  party would have thier feast first; and they told him what they had got,  and how the owners of the malt had been driven off, and how the bridegroom  had jumped into the water. When Thorir heard the story he said, Do you  think you have made a good business of it now, that you laugh so heartily?  How do you suppose you will get out of it? Do you imagine you will sleep  quietly here to-night and want nothing else? Do you not know what Glums  disposition will be, if he approves of his kinsmans journey? I say it  is good counsel to get our men together; it is most probable that Glum  has already assembled a good many of his.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>There was at that time  a ford in the river at the place where now there is none. In the course  of the night they collected some eighty good men, and stationed them on  the edge of the rising ground, because the ford was just at that very  point. On the other hand, it is to be told how Arnor found Glum and gave  him an account of his expedition. Yes, answered Glum, this is pretty  much what I expected; I did not think they would be quiet; and the matter  is somewhat difficult to handle. If we do nothing there is disgrace for  us, and the honour is not so clear if we try to set it right. However,  we must get our men together. So when day broke Glum came to the river  with sixty men and wanted to ride across, but the men of Espihole pelted  them with stones, so that they did not advance; and Glum turned back whilst  they fought with stones and missiles across the water. A good many men  were wounded, but their names are not recorded. When the men of the district  became aware of what was going on they came up in the course of the day  and interfered, and the two parties came to a parley about terms. The  men of Espihole were asked what satisfaction they would make for the insult  offered to Arnor, and they said that no satisfaction was due from them,  though Arnor had run away from his malt-sacks. Then a proposal was made  that Glum should take part in asking, on behalf of Thorgrim, for Herpruda,  the other daughter of Gizor, and that the marriage of Arnor and Thordis  should take place only on condition of Glums getting this second match  agreed to. In fact, the one who was to be married to Thogrim was thought  to have the best bargain. In consequence of the intervention of so many  people, Glum promised his assistance in this matter, and he went to Gizor  and spoke to him upon it. It may seem, he said, to be officiousness  on my part, if I take on myself to woo a wife for my own kinsman and for  the men of Espihole too; but in order to stop disturbances in our district,  I think I am bound to pledge my faith and friendship to you, if you will  do as I wish. Gizpr replied, It seems best to me that you should have  you way, inasmuch as the offer to my daughter is a good one; and so both  matches were agreed on. Arnor went to live at Upsal, and Thorgrim at Mödrufell.  Shortly after this Gizor died, and Saldis moved her household to Upsal.  Arnor had a son by Thordis, who was called Steinolf, and Thorgrim had  one who was named Arngrim, and was, as he grew up, a promising lad.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="12" title="">
   <paragraph>Saldis invited  both her grandsons to stay with her. Arngrim was two winters older than  Steinolf; there was not in the whole of the Eyjafirth any boys of a better  disposition or greater promise, and they were very fond of each other.  When one was four years old and the other six, they were one day playing  together, and Steinolf asked Arngrim to lend him the little brass horse  which he had. Arngrim answered, I will give it you, for looking to my  age, it is more fit for your plaything than mine. Steinolf went and told  his foster-mother what a fair gift he had got, and she said it was quite  right that they should be on such good terms with one another.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>There was a woman who  went about in that part of the country, named Oddbiörg, who amused people  by story telling, and was a spaewife. A feeling existed that it was  of some consequence for the mistress of the house to receive her well,  for that what she said depended more or less on how she was entertained.  She came to Upsal, and Saldis asked her to spae something, and that something  good, of those boys. Her answer was, Hopeful are these lads; but what  their future luck may be it is difficult for me to discern. Saldis exclaimed,  If I am to judge by this unsatisfactory speech of yours, I suppose you  are not pleased with your treatment here. You must not, said Oddbiörg,  let this affect your hospitality, nor need you be so particular about  a word of this kind. The less you say the better, replied Saldis, if  you can tell us nothing good. I have not yet said too much, she answered;  but I do not think this love of theirs will last long. Then Saldis said,  I should have thought my good treatment of you deserved some other omen;  and if you deal with evil bodings, you will have a chance of being turned  out of doors. Well, said Oddbiörg, since you are so angry about nothing,  I see no need for sparing you, and I shall never trouble you again. But,  take it as you will, I can tell you that these boys will hereafter be  the death each of the other, and one mischief worse than another for this  district will spring from them. So Oddbiörg is out of our story.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="13" title="">
   <paragraph>It happened  one summer, at the Althing, that the Northern men and those of the West-firths  met one another on the wrestling ground in a match according to their  districts. The Northerners had rather the worst of it, and their leader  was Márr, the son of Glum. Now a certain man of the name of Ingolf, the  son of Thorvald, came up, whose father lived at Rangavellir. Márr addressed  him thus--You are a strong-limbed fellow, and ought to be sturdy; do  me the favour of going into the match and taking hold. his answer was--I  will do so for your sake, and forthwith the man he grappled with went  down, and thus it was with the second, and the third, so that the Northerners  were well pleased. Then said Márr, If you want a good word on my part,  I shall be ready to help you. What may be your plans? I have no plans,  he answered, but I had an inclination to go northward and get work.  Well, rejoined Márr, I should like you to go with me; I will get you  a place. Ingolf had a good horse of his own, which he called b the name  of Snækoll, and he went northward to Thverá, after the Thing was over,  and staid there some time. Márr asked him one day what he intended to  do. There is and over-looker wanted here, who ought to be somewhat handy;  for instance, here is this sledge to be finished, and if you can do that  you can do something worth having. I should be too glad of such a place,  said Ingolf, but it has sometimes happened that my horses have caused  trouble in the pastures of the cattle. No one will talk about that here,  answered Márr; so Ingiolf set to work on the sledge. Glum came up, and  looked at what he was doing. That is a good piece of work, he observed.  What are your plans? Ingolf answered, I have no plans. Glum replied,  I want an over-looker, are you used to that sort of business? Not much,  in such a place as this, but I should be glad to stay with you. Why  should it not be so? said Glum; for I see that you and Márr get on well  together. When Márr came home Ingolf told him what had passed. I should  like it much, he answered, if it turns out well, and I will take care,  if anything displeases my father, to tell you of it three times; but if  you do not set it right then I must stop. So Ingolf took to his business,  and Glum was pleased with him.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>One day Glum and Ingolf,  his over-looker, went to a horse-fight; the latter rode a mare, but the  horse ran along by their side. The sport was good; Kálf, of Stockahlad  was there, and he had an old working horse who beat all the others. He  called out, why dont they bring into the ring that fine-jawed beast  of the Thverá people? They are no fair match, said Glum, your cart-horse  and that stallion. Ah! exclaimed Kálf, the real reason why you will  not fight him is because he has no spirit in him. It may be the old proverb  is proved true, the cattle are like their master. You know nothing  about that, answered Glum, and I will not refuse on Ingolfs part, but  the fight must not go on longer than he chooses. He will probably know  well enough, said Kálf, that little will be done against your wishes,  The two horses were led out, and fought well, and all thought Ingolfs  horse had the best of it; Glum then chose to separate them, and they rode  home. Ingolf remained that year in his place, and Glum was well satisfied  with him.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Not long after this there  was a meeting at Diupadal, whither Glum, and Ingolf with his horse, came;  Kálf also was there. This last man was a friend of the people of Espihole,  and he demanded that they should now let the horses fight it out. Glum  said it depended on Ingolf, but that he himself was against it; howerer,  he did not like to back out of it, and the horses were led out accordingly.  Kálf spurred his horse on, but Ingolfs horse had the best of it in every  contest. Then Kálf struck Ingolfs horse over the ears with his staff  in such a way as to make him giddy, but immediately afterwards he went  at his adversary again. Glum came up, and fair fighting was restore, till  in the end Kálfs horse bolted from the ring. Then there wars a great  shout, and at last Kálf smote Ingolf with his stick. People interfered,  and Glum said, Let us take no note of such a matter as this; this is  the end of every horse-fight. Márr, on the other hand, said to Ingolf,  Depend upon it, my father does not intend that any disgrace shall attach  to you for this blow.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="14" title="">
   <paragraph>There was  a man named Thorkel, who lived at Hamar. Ingolf went thither, and met  this mans daughter, who was a handsome woman. Her father was well enough  off, but he was not a person of much consideration in the country. Ingolf,  however, attended properly to his duties as over-looker, but he did not  work as a craftsman so much as he had done, and Márr spoke to him once  about it saying, I see that my father is not pleased at your being often  away from home. Ingolf gave a fair answer, but it came to the same thing  again, and Márr warned him again a second and third time, but it was no  use.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>One evening it happened  that he came home late, and when the men had had their supper Glum said,  Now let us amuse ourselves, and let each of us say what or whom he most  relies on, and I will have first choice. Well, I choose three things on  which I most rely; the first is my purse, the second is my axe, and the  third is my larder. Then one man after another made his choice, and Glum  called out, whom do you chose, Ingolf? His answer was, Thorkel, of  Hamar. Glum jumped up, held up a the hilt of his sword, and going up  to him said, A pretty sort of patron you have chosen. All men saw  that Glum was wroth. He went out, and Ingolf went with him, and then Glum  said to him, Go now to your patron and tell him you have killed Kálf.  Why, replied he, how can I tell him this lie? You shall do as I please,  answered Glum, so they both went together, and Glum turned into the barn,  where he saw a calf before him. Cut its head off, he cried, and then  go southward across the river and tell Thorkel that you look to him alone  for protection, and show him your bloody sword as the token of the deed  you have done. Ingolf did this; went to Thorkel, and told him as news  how he had not forgooten the blow Kálf had given him, and how he had killed  him. The answer was, You are a fool, and you have killed a good man;  get you gone as quick as you can, I do not choose that you should be slain  on my premises. Then Ingolf came back again to meet Glum, who asked him  Well, how did your patron turn out? Not over well, said he. You will  have trouble on your hands, remarked Glum, if Kálf, of Stockahlad should  really be killed.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Now Glum himself had killed  Kálf, at Stöckahlad, whilst Ingolf was away, and had thus taken  vengeance for him,  and  the following day Kálfs death was publicly known. Thorkel said at once  that a fellow had come thither who had taken the death on himself, so  that everybody thought it was really so. The winter passed on, and Glum  sent Ingolf northward, to the house of Einar, the son of Konál, and gave  him nine hundred ells of cloth. You have had no wages, he said, from  me, but with your saving habits you may turn this to good account, and  as regards this matter which is laid to your charge I will take care of  that. It shall not hurt you; I paid you off for your perverseness in this  way, and when you come home you may come and pay me a visit. Ingolf answered,  One thing I beg of you, do not let the woman be married to any one else.  This, I promise you, said Glum. Ingolfs horses were left where they  were. Einar, the son of Konál, got Ingolf conveyed abroad, but Thorvald  began a suit at the Hegranes Thing for the slaughter of Kálf, and it looked  as if Ingolf would be found guilty. Glum was at the Thing, and some of  Ingolfs kinsmen came to him, and asked him to look after the case, professing  their readiness to contribute to pay the fine for him. Glum told them,  I will se to the suit without any fine being paid.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>When the court went out  to sit, and the defendant was called on for his defence, Glum stated that  the suit was null and void, for you have proceeded against the wrong  man; I did the deed. Then he named his witnesses, who were to certify  that the suit was void; for though Ingolf did kill the calf in the  barn, I did not make any charge against him for that. Now, I will offer  an atonement more according to the worth of the man killed, ant according  to the pride of you men of Espihole. So he did, and the people left the  Thing.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Ingolf was abroad that  winter, and could stand it no longer, but turned his cash into goods,  and purchased valuable articles, and tapestry hangings of rare quality.  Glum had given him a good cloak, and he exchanged that for a scarlet kirtle.  The summer that he had sailed there came out to Iceland the man called  Thiodolf, whose mother lived at Æsustad. He visited Hamar, and fell in  with Helga. One day Glum was riding up to Hole, and a he went down the  hill at Saurbæ, Thiodolf met him. Glum said to him, I do not like your  visits to Hamar; I mean myself to provide for Helgas marriage, and if  you do not give this up I shall challenge you to the Holmgang. He answered  that he was not going to math himself with Glum, and so he left off going  thither.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="15" title="">
   <paragraph>Then Ingolf  came out to Iceland and went to Thverá, and asked Glum to take him in,  which was granted. One day he said, Now, Glum, I should like you to look  over my merchandize. So he did, and it seemed to him that Ingolf had  laid out his money well. Then Ingolf said, You gave me the capital for  this voyage, and I consider all the goods as belonging to you. No,  answered Glum, what you have got is not enough for me to take anything  from you. Here, answered Ingolf, are some hangings which I purchased  for you--these you shall accept; and here is a kirtle. I will accept  your gifts, replied Glum.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Another time Glum asked  him if he wished to remain at home with him, and Ingolf answered that  his intention was not to part from him if he had the choice o staying.  My stud-horses I will give you, he said, and Glum replied, The horses  I will accept, and now to-day we will go and find Thorkel, at Hamar.  Thorkel received Glum well, and the latter said, You have wronged Ingolf,  and now you must make it up to him by giving him your daughter in marriage--he  is a proper man for this match. I will lay down some money for him, and  I have proved him to be a worthy fellow. If you do not act thus, you will  see that you have made a bad business of it. So Thorkel consented, and  Ingolf got his wife and settled down as a householder and a good useful  man.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="16" title="">
   <paragraph>Glum married  his daughter Thorlauga to Vigu-Skuta, of Myvatn, in the north country,  but on account of disagreement the husband caused her to return to Thverà,  and divorced her, which annoyed Glum much. Afterwards Arnor Kerlingarnef  wooed her and had her to wife, and good men are sprung from that marriage.  From this time there was a great feud between Glum and Skuta. One summer  it happened that a vagabond fellow came to Skuta and asked to be taken  in. He inquired what he had been doing, and the answered was that he had  slain a man and could not stay in the district to which he belonged. Skuta  replied, Well, what are you ready to do to earn my protection? What  do you ask for? said the other. Why, you shall go, as sent from me,  to Glums house, and tell him that you want him to take charge of your  affair. I think it will turn out with reference to your meeting that he  is now on his way to the Thing. He is a good man to help any one in trouble,  if people want his aid; and it may be that he will tell you to go to Thverà  and wait for him there. You will then say that you are in too great a  strait for this, and that you would rather have some talk with him alone,  and it may be that he will tell you what to do. An any rate ask him to  let you meet in the Midárdal, which runs up from the homestead at Thverà  and in which his pasture-huts stand; say that you would be glad to find  him there on some day named for the purpose. The man assented to all  this, and it was arranged as Skuta had proposed. Now this fellow, who  was to serve as a bait, came back to Skuta and told him the whole. You  have done your work well, said he, and you had better stay with me.  Time passed on until the day came when Glum had promised the meeting,  and then Skuta gets ready to start from home with thirty men. He rides  southward, and then west, over the heath of Vadla, and so on to the bank  which is called Red-bank, and there they dismount. Then Skuta says to  his men, You will have to stay here a little while, and I will ride further  into the valley, along the side of the hill, to see if there is anything  to be got. When he looks along the valley he sees a tall man, in a green  cloak, riding up from Thverà, whom he knows to be Glum, and gets off his  horse. He has a cape on him of two colours, one side black and the other  white, and he leaves his horse in the clearing and goes up to the pasture-hut  into which Glum has entered. Skuta holds in his hand the sword named Fluga,  with a helmet on his head; he goes up to the door, knocks upon the wall,  and then steps on one side close to the hut. Glum comes out, without any  weapon in his hand, and sees no one by the hut, but Skuta rushes forward  between Glum and the doorway. Then Glum knows his man, and starts away  from him. The gorge in which the river runs is near the hut. Skuta calls  to him to wait, but he says it would be all right if they were armed in  the same way, and makes for the gorge with Skuta after him. Glum jumps  right into the gorge, but Skuta looks about to see where he can get down.  Then he sees in the gorge a cloak driven along in the water, and runs  towards it, thrusting at it with his sword; but he hears a voice calling  out above him, There is little honour to be won by spoiling peoples  clothes. He looks up and recognizes Glum; who in fact knew that there  was a grassy bank on the edge of the stream where he jumped down. Well,  says Skuta, remember one thing, Glum, you have run for it, and would  not wait for Skuta. Glums answer is, That is true enough, and I only  wish that, before sunset this day, you may have to run for it as far as  I have done. Glum sung a verse--</paragraph>
   <poetry>
    <line>South of the river here, I trow,</line>
    <line>Each bush is worth a crown;</line>
    <line>Elsewhere the forest often saves</line>
    <line>The outlaw hunted down.</line>
   </poetry>
   <paragraph>So they parted at that time;  but Glum went home, got his people together, told them what a trap had  been set for him, and expressed his desire to take vengeance for it at  once. In a short time he collected sixty men and rode up into the valley.  Skuta, after parting with Glum, got back to his horse, and riding along  the hill-side he saw the men on their way. He thought it would not be  good for him to meet them, so he made his plan, broke his spear-head off  its shaft, handled this as if it were a pole, unsaddled his horse and  rode bareback, with his cape turnd inside out, shouting as if he were  looking for sheep. Glums men overtook him and inquired if he had seen  any man fully armed riding over the hill? He replied that he had seen  one. What is your name? they asked. I am called, he says, Plenty  in the Myvatn country, but at Fiskelæk people call me Scarce. They  answered, You are making sport of us; but he said he could not tell  them anything truer than what he had told them, and so he parted from  them. As soon as this was done he took up his daddle again and rode sharply  off to his own men. Glums people came up to him and told him they had  met a man who had answered them with a jest, and they said what his name  was. You have made a blunder, said Glum; it was Skuta himself that  you fell in with. What could he say that was more true? In the Myvatn  country caves (Skuta) are plenty, and in Fiskelæk they are scarce.  He has come pretty close to us, and we must ride after him. So they came  up to the bank where Skuta and his men were, but there was only one path  up to it, and the position was easier to defend with thirty men that it  was to attack with sixty. Skuta then called out, You have taken a good  deal of trouble to follow me up, and I suppose you think you haves something  to pay me for on account of your escape. No doubt you showed great presence  of mind in jumping into the gorge, and you were pretty quick of foot about  it. Yes, said Glum, and you had some reason to be afraid when you  pretended to be a sheperd belonging to the Eyjafirth people, and hid your  arms or broke some of them. I fancy you had to run quite as far as I did.  Skuta replied, However things may have gone up this time, try now to  attack us with double our number. Glums answer was, I think we will  part this time, whatever people may say of either of us. So Skuta rode  away north, and Glum went home to Thverà.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="17" title="">
   <paragraph>When Thorir  died his son Thorarin set up his household to the north of Espihole and  lived there. Glum had two children by his wife, of whom one was Márr,  as has been said above, and the other was Vigfuss; both promising, but  utterly unlike each other. Márr was quiet and silent, but Vigfuss was  a dashing fellow, ready to do an unfair thing, strong and full of courage.  There was a man living with Glum, who was called Hallvard, and was a freedman  of his; he had brought Vigfuss up, and having got a good deal of property  together by cheating in money matters , he had made over the reversion  if it to his foster-child. Hallvard had a bad name, and went to live at  a place called The Tarns, in the valley of the Eyjafirth: nor did his  reputation impove on account of the spot where he dwelt, for he was sharp  in dealing with the cattle in the common pastures up there. Vigfuss was  a great traveller</paragraph>
   <paragraph>A man hight Halli lived  at Jorunnarstad, who was called Halli the white, and he was the son  of Thorbiörn, whilst his mother was Vigdis, the daughter of Andun the  bald. Now Halli had fostered Einar, the son of Eyiolf, who then lived  at Saurbæ. Halli was blind, and was mixed up in all the lawsuits in the  country because he was both a wise man and sound in his judgment. His  sons were Orm and Brusi the Skald, who lived at Törfufell, and Bárd, who  lived at Skállstad. Bárd was a noisy, quarrelsome fellow, better able  to fight than anybody, and reckless and abusive in his language; he had  for a wife Una, the daughter of Oddkell, in Thiorsádal.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>One autumn Halli missed  some ten or twelve wethers out of the hill pastures, and they could not  be found, so when Bárd and his father met, Halli asked his son what he  thought had become of the wethers. Bárd replied, I dont wonder if sheep  disappear, when a thief lives next door to you, ever since Hallvard came  into the district. Yes, says Halli, I should like you to set on foot  a suit against him, and summon him for theft. I dont think, if I make  this charge against him, Glum will go the lengths of clearing him by the  oath of twelve men. No, answered Bárd, it will be a difficult matter  for him to get the oath of twelve men out of Glum and Vigfuss and their  people.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="18" title="">
   <paragraph>Then Bárd  set his suit on foot, and when Vigfuss knew it, he told his father that  he should not like proceedings for a theft to be commenced against his  foster-father. Glums answer was, You know he is not to be trusted, and  it will not be a popular thing to swear him guiltless. Vigfuss said,  Then I would rather that we had to deal with a matter of greater consequence.  Glum replied, It seems to me better to pay something on his account and  let him change his residence and come hither, than to risk my credit for  a man of his character.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>When men came up to the  Thing, the case was brought on in court, and Glum had to swear one way  or the other with his twelve men. Vigfuss became aware of the fact that  his father intended to find Hallvard guilty, so he went to the court and  said that he would take care Glum should pay dearly for it, if his foster-father  was declared guilty. It ended in Glum quashing the suit by swearing that  Hallvard was innocent, and he got discredit by doing so. In the course  of a winter or two it happened that Halli lost a pig of his, which was  so fat that it could hardly get on its legs. Bárd came in one day and  asked if he pig had been killed, and Halli said it had disappeared. Bárd  replied, he is gone, no doubt, to look for the sheep which were stolen  last autumn. I suppose, said Halli, they are both gone the same way.  Will you summon Hallvard? Well, replied Bárd, so it shall be, for  I do not think Glum will this time swear Hallvard free; Vigfuss was the  cause of he previous acquittal, and he is not now in the country. Bárd  took up the case and proceeded to serve the summons; but when he met Hallvard  he made a short matter of the suit by cutting of his head, and went and  told his father. Halli did not like it; he straightway found Glum, told  him what had happened, and offered to leave the matter in his hands. Glum  accepted the offer, assessed the damage at a small sum, and caused the  pig and the sheep to be paid for, by doing which he was well spoken of.  When Vigfuss returned he was displeased at Hallvards death; but his father  said, I shall not allow this settlement to be disturbed now it is made;  and when Vigfuss and Bárd met nothing passed between them.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>The next summer there  was a meeting appointed for a horse-fight, in which all the horses in  that district were to be fought; those from the upper against those from  the lower rape, and  either party were to select their man as umpire to decide which had the  best of it. The judgment of the men thus chosen was to be abided by. From  the upper rape Bárd was taken, and from the lower Vigfuss, the son of  Glum. There were many horses, and the sport was good, but the fight was  pretty equal, and many matches came off, with the result however that  the number of those which fought well, and those which bolted was the  same. so they agreed that it was an equal match; but Vigfuss said he had  a horse which had not fought, which was the best on the ground that day.  Come, said he, do you match some one with him. Bárd answered, He  looks a poor beast to us, we will not match any horse with him; let us  say it is a tie. Oh, replied Vigfuss, the fact is you have none to  meet him, but you do not choose to own that you have got the worst of  it. Up to this time, said Bárd, You have acted impartially, but now  the sky is clouding over. Now we see the truth, that you have stood by  your mother at the dresser in the pantry, and talked about cooking oftener  than you have been at horse-fights, and that is the reason why your beard  has never got any colour in it. Vigfuss and other people laughed at this  joke.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Hallis servant came home,  and his mater asked him about the horse-fights. He said the match was  held to be a tie. Then Halli asked, Did Bárd and Vigfuss agree? Yes,  pretty well, but Bárd said one thing to Vigfuss. What was that? he  inquired; then the servant repeated it, and Halli said, That will lead  to mischief. The servant said, Vigfuss laughed at it. Yes, but it  is the way of Glum and his son to laugh when the fit for killing somebody  comes upon them.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>When Halli and Bárd met,  the former asked his son, How came you to talk in that reckless way?  I fear it will lead to great evil. You have but one thing to do, and that  is to go abroad and get house timber; you must stay away three winters  or your death is certain. Bárd answered, There is nothing in it if you  were not a coward, but old age causes you to be afraid on account of your  sons. You are no doubt a very brave fellow, said Halli, but you will  find it difficult to stay in the district. So Bárd took his fathers  advice and went abroad, and Halli bribed a vagrant fellow to go into Skagafirth,  or to the westward of it, and tell the story how Bárd was gone away; and  how for the sake of one word, on account of Glum and his son, the only  safe course for him had been to become an exile; and ho no one in the  district dared to do anything which they disliked. This fellow did what  Halli wished, and they had recourse to this plan in order that Bárds  kinsmen might not be molested for his sake. Bárd stopped out one winter,  and then returned to his home.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="19" title="">
   <paragraph>Whilst Bárd  was away Halli took care of his property, and got some timber cut in a  wood in Midárdal which belonged to him, and Bárd brought out a good deal  of timber with him. Sometimes he stayed at his own home, and sometimes  with his father. Bárd said he would go and fetch his timber home, when  Halli remarked, I would not have you go yourself, for it is not good  to trust that father and son. Oh, said Bárd, nobody will know that  I am going. So he went, and a servant with him, to fetch the timber,  and they took a good many horses with them, but his wife Una had gone  to Vidines to see her sister Oddkatla, and Bárd went thither on his way.  Hlenni begged him to send some one else into the wood, and to stay where  he was himself; it seemed more prudent to do so, but Bárd answered there  was no need of it.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>The two sisters went with  him out of the homestead, but when they were returning Una looked back  at him over her shoulder, and fell down in a swoon. Her sister asked her  what she had seen? I saw dead men coming to meet Bárd, said she; he  must be fey. We shall never see one another again. Bárd and his men  made their way into the wood, and when they were there, they got their  loads of timber together, and tied up their horses, but a great mist had  come on. Very early that morning the shepherd from Thverà had been a-foot,  and Vigfuss met him and asked him for tidings, as he often did. It is  wonderful to me, he said, that you never fail to find your sheep in  such a fog as there is now. The shepherd answered, It is a small matter  for me to find my flock, but those men whom I saw in the wood in the morning  had more trouble to find their horses, which were really standing close  to them. They were fine looking fellows; one was in a green kirtle, and  they had shields by their sides. Vigfuss asked him if he knew the man?  He said he thought it was Bárd, for he was the owner of the wood where  they were. Get my three horses, said Vigfuss. There were two Easterlings  staying there whom Vigfuss asked to ride with him, saying that he was  going to the warm spring; but when he got out of the homestead he made  as if he would ride southward over Laugardal. The Easterlings asked him,  Whither are you riding now? On some business of my own first, said  he, so he rode a good way in front of them, and they went southward above  the enclosures, until they saw Bárd coming out of the wood with his loaded  horses. Bárds servant saw some one riding after them, and remarked, These  men are riding sharp after us. Who is that? said Bárd. It is Vigfuss,  he replied, and I think we had better get away from him. There is no  disgrace in doing so, whilst we know nothing of their intentions. Bárd  said, He will not set on me with three men, if you are not with me.  I would sooner go with the horses, answered the man, and do you ride  to Vidines. You cannot be blamed for going where you have business, and  you do not know for a certainty what they who are riding after us want,  thought Hlenni told you not to trust them. Bárd told him then, You shall  ride on forward and, if I am delayed, tell our men what is going on, for  it is likely that I and Vigfuss shall be some time about it, if we look  one another fairly in the face; and he is too good a man to set on me  with three against one. If, on the other hand, we are two and they are  three, they will take the benefit of the difference in strength.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>The servant did what Bárd  told him, and Bárd himself unstrapped his shield, and got ready in the  best way he could. When they came up he asked what they wanted? Vigfuss  said that both of them would not quit the meeting-place alive. Bárd replied  that he was ready, if they two only were to play the game out; but there  is no manhood in it if three are to set on one. The Easterlings then  said they would have staid at home if they had known their errand, but  that they could not take part unless, in consequence of Bárds companion  having ridden off, men should come to his assistance. Vigfuss told them  to see first how matters went. So he and Bárd fought for some time without  either being wounded, but it looked worse for Vigfuss, inasmuch as he  had to give ground every time without being able to make a single blow  tell. Bárd had his sword, and defended himself admirable without being  touched. In the mean time the Easterlings thought it would be a bad business  if Vigfuss should be slain, while they stood by doing nothing, and if  men should come up to help Bárd. They they rushed at him, so that he was  dying when Hlenni and his men got there. Vigfuss and his friends rode  home, but Glum was ill pleased with what they had done, and said that  the difficulties in the district would be greatly increased. Halli went  to his foster-son Einar, at Saurbæ, and asked him to take the case in  hand, and he admitted that he was bound to avenge his kinsman and foster-brother.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Then they rode to Thorarin, and asked for his support; he replied that  he knew no man he would rather have to deal with than Vigfuss, and they  confirmed with oaths their alliance with reference to that and all other  matters. The cause went to the Thing, and attempts were made to compound  it, but there was so much in the way that it was difficult to effect a  compromise, as both the men of Mödrufell and those of Espihole, who resisted  it, were bold in spirit, and well versed in the law. The case was closed  by a verdict against the Easterlings, and by money being given to allow  Vigfuss a safe conduct. He was to have three summers to get a passage  out, and to have three places of refuge in each year, but he was an outlaw  on peril of his life elsewhere, and not allowed to be at home on account  of the sacredness of the place. However, he stayed long at Upsal, though  people thought he was in other quarters of the island, and he would not  go abroad within the period fixed. Then he became completely outlawed,  and Glum kept him concealed, but outlawed men were not allowed to live  there because Frey, who owned the temple, did not permit it. So matters  went on for six winters.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="20" title="">
   <paragraph>We must now go back to the point where the foster-brothers Arngrim and Steinolf  were growing up together. When Thorgrim of Mödrufell died, Arngrim went  to his own house, and Steinolf remained with him, and there was as much  affection between them as there had ever been. Arngrim took a wife, Thordis,  the daughter of Biörn, and the sister of Arnor Kerlingarnef. Steinolf  was at that time abroad, engaged in trading voyages, but when he was in  Iceland he was at Arngrims house. It happened one summer, on his arrival  in the Eyjafirth, that Arngrim did not invite him to his house, and though  they met he did not speak to him, imputing to him that he had talked with  his wife, Thordis, more than was proper; but the report of most men was  that there was little or nothing in the matter. Then Glum asked Steinolf  to visit him, and he was there for a year or two when he was in Iceland,  and they regarded one another with much affection as kinsmen. Steinolf  was an active merry fellow. One summer Glum did not ask him to his house,  and said that he preferred that he should be with his father at Upsal,  and my reason is, I do not approve of men living in other peoples house,  but if you are with your father then you can come over hither to Thverà,  and I shall be glad to see you. Vigfuss, for some winters, whilst he  was an outlaw, was at Upsal with Arnor Red-cheek, and Steinolf was there  also. One autumn a yeoman at Öxnafell married his daughter, and invited  all those land-owners in Eyjafirth, who were of most consequence; Steinolf  too was invited. He came over to Thverà, and wanted to go with Glum, bout  Glum said he should not be at the wedding. Then Steinolf observed, What  I do not like is that you do not abide by what you say. Well, said  Glum, my want of consistency will not do so much harm as your want of  prudence, and I will not go. It is a piece of presumption at any rate,  if there is no deeper design in it, for a yeoman to ask so many men of  consequence to his house. But I suspect that something more is meant that  appears, and that the yeoman did not get up this scheme himself, so I  think it better that I and my friends should stay away. Steinolf, however,  and those who were asked, with the exception of Glum, went to the wedding.  Einar, the son of Eyiolf, Thorvald, and Steingrim had a good deal of talk  together. When people were going away, Einar made a long speech about  the management of affairs in the district, and said it was fitting that  when they met in any number they should talk over the matters of most  urgency; that in this way things would get into a better state. For instance,  he said, there has long been a bad feeling among men of the highest spirit,  and I allude particularly to the fact that there is a quarrel between  the two kinsmen Arngrim and Steinolf, whilst we think that some lie or  calumny is at the bottom of it all. Now Arngrim wishes to invite Steinolf  to his house, and will receive him honourably if he choose to accept the  invitation. So get rid of all unfriendly feeling between you. Steinolf  professed his readiness to accept the offer, and his unconsciousness of  any cause of offence, and he added that he loved Arngrim above all men.  The each man returned to his home, and Steinolf went back with Arngrim,  and remained with him, for several nights with all honour.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="21" title="">
   <paragraph>One day  Arngrim asked Steinolf if he would go down with him to Grund to a club-feast,  and stay two or three nights. He replied, I will stay at home now and  go some other time when you are here. Arngrim expressed a hope that he  would wait for his return, if he would not accompany him, and he went  on to Grund, but Steinolf stayed over the night. In the morning Steinolf  was sitting by the fire, with some work in hand; it was a certain casket  which belonged to the lady of the house. At that moment Arngrim returned  home with Thorvald the crooked, and as they came into the sitting-room  Steinolf was bending down over his work. Then Arngrim struck him on the  head in such a way as to cause his death; but the mistress of the house  came up to him and exclaimed, Wretch that thou are to strike this blow!  This is the work of wiser men than thou art; but from this day I will  never be they wife. She went to the house of Arnor Kerlingarnef and never  came together with Arngrim again; but before she rode off she said, It  will be some consolation, Arngrim, that your days are to be few, for those  which are to come will be worse for you. Afterwards she became the wife  of Asgrim, Ellidagrims son.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Arngrim and Thorvald rode  to Espihole and told Thorarin what had happened, asking for his protection,  and adding that whilst they had neither the wisdom nor the popularity  to hold their own against Glum, he (Thorarin) had abundance of both. He  replied to them and said that the deed seemed to be bad, and one from  which apprehended evil consequences. Thorvald thought it was no use to  find fault with what had been done, and that if he did not support them,  he would soon have greater difficulties on his hands. They hoped to get  other people to help them, if he would speak on their behalf. My counsel,  says Thorarin, is that you should both remove from Grund and Mödrufell,  and that we should collect men as soon as we may, and join our households  together, before Glum is informed of it. They did this before Glum heard  what had occurred; but when he learnt it he assembled his people, who  proceeded to attack them. However, there was no opportunity for doing  so with effect, as the men of Espihole had the larger force, and so they  remained quiet for the winter. Glum, on the other hand, was never to be  got at; he was so cautious about himself that he never slept in the bed  which had been prepared for him. Very often he rested little at night,  but he and Márr walked up and down and talked about lawsuits. One night  Márr asked him how he had slept, and Glum answered by a stanza--</paragraph>
   <poetry>
    <line>Mid all this strife and tumult now</line>
    <line>Sleep doth mine eyelids flee.</line>
    <line>These men will find it hard, I trow,</line>
    <line>To make their peace with me,</line>
   </poetry>
   <poetry>
    <line>Before upon their crests shall ring</line>
    <line>My sword in battle-fray.</line>
    <line>Ive slain men for a small thing,</line>
    <line>And why not these, I pray?</line>
   </poetry>
   <paragraph>Now I will tell you of my  dream. Methought I went out of the homestead here by myself and without  arms, and Thorarin seemed to come at me with a large whetstone in his  hand, and I felt ill prepared for our meeting; but whilst I was thinking  about it I saw another whetstone lying close by me, so I cuaght it up  and attacked him, and when we met either tried to strike the other, but  the two stones came against one another and there was a tremendous crash.  Was it such, asked Márr, as might be considered a conflict between  the two houses? More than that, replied Glum. Did it seem that it  might represent a conflict between the two districts? Yes, said Glum,  the omen may well be reckoned such, for I thought the crash could be  heard all over the district, and when I woke I sung as follows</paragraph>
   <poetry>
    <line>I thought this night to see in sleep</line>
    <line>that chief, who o'er the sea</line>
    <line>guides the fierce raven of the deep,</line>
    <line>Smite with a stone at me.</line>
   </poetry>
   <poetry>
    <line>The lord of Limafirths broad strand</line>
    <line>Came on in all his pride,</line>
    <line>I met him fearless hand to hand</line>
    <line>And dashd the blow aside.</line>
   </poetry>
   <paragraph>Márr observed it was very likely the old saying would come true,  Each of you will smite the other with and evil stone before it is over.  Yes, said Glum, it is not improbable; there are many bodings tending that  way. There is another dream to tell you. Methought I was standing out of  doors, and that I saw two women who had a trough between them, and they  took their stations at Hrisateig and sprinkled the whole district with blood.  I woke up, and I think this portends  something which is to happen. Then  I sung these verses--</paragraph>
   <poetry>
    <line>The gods--methought, they swept along</line>
    <line>Across the path of men.</line>
    <line>the clash of swords and the javelins song</line>
    <line>We shall hear full soon again.</line>
   </poetry>
   <poetry>
    <line>I saw the maids of carnage stand,</line>
    <line>In grim and vengeful mood,</line>
    <line>As the battle ragd, and they drenchd the land</line>
    <line>In slaughterd warriors blood.</line>
   </poetry>
   <paragraph>That morning Márr rode to  Mödrufell, with seventeen other men, to summon Arngrim for the death of  Steinolf; but Glum remained at home with five men besides himself, and  told them to be quick in getting back again. In the house with Glum were  Jöd, and Eyiolf, the son of Thorleif the tall, Thorvald Tafalld, Glums  nephew, and two thralls.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="22" title="">
   <paragraph>Helga, Glum's  sister, who had been married to Steingrim of Sigluvik, had at that time  come to Laugaland; she was the mother of Thorvald Tafalld, who was then  eighteen years of age. There was a man named Thorvard, the son of Ornolf  and of Yngvillda, who went by the name of Everybodys sister. He lived  at Krisnes, and had a son named Gudbrand, who was then twelve years old.  Thorvard was a prudent man, and tolerably well inclined to help any one,  but he was then old. That morning he was early a-foot, and told his man  to get his horses. Then they rode to Thverà, and when they got there Márr  had just started. Glum welcomed Thorvard well, and the latter inquired  if any attempt had been made to procure a settlement between the parties.  Glum told him None. Thorvard asked, Is the suit set on foot? Glum  said it was not. Then said the other, A day like this would be a good  one for this business: there is much mist, and no one would know what  was going on, if one went quietly about it. Glum went on to say how matters  stood, and how six men only remained at home. Thorvard answered, You  have rather a small number with you, but the steps you have taken will  no doubt be sufficient. Then Thorvard rode to Espihole, and when he came  thither the men were not up; but he found Thorarin, and inquired, What  do you intend to do? Do you intend to offer Glum any composition for the  death? Thorarin answered, We do not think it an easy matter to offer  to compound with Glum. Is the suit set on foot? asked Thorvard. I  have not heard, said Thorarin; but what do you know about the matter?  Oh, replied he, Márr rode off this morning with seventeen others to  proceed with the suit, and Glum remained at home with five men; no doubt  it would now be a famous chance for setting matters straight, but you  fellows here never get the best of it, because you are not so sharp in  your movements as Glum is. Well, said Thorarin, the fact is I do not  like to set up mere gossip and nonsense on our side to meet this charge.  Thorvard answered, Whether there was any sufficient cause or not is a  point which ought to have been considered before Steinolf was killed.  Did he not try to seduce Arngrims wife? Of a surety I think such a matter  as that is not to be reckoned as nothing. Thorarin persisted, I do not  like having to do with such a business. What do you mean, said Thorvard,  by talking thus? Glum got something by that outlawry of your relative,  Sigmund, and your clear course is not to let yourself be thus insulted  by him. I am not sure, said Thorarin, whether that is or is not a  wise course.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>After this conversation  the people of the house got up, and Thorvald the crooked pressed that  they should ride to Upsal and give notice of outlawry as against Steinolf  for his conduct to Arngrims wife, so that he might be taken to have been  rightly killed. Thorarin said, That does not seem very advisable, but  we will do it. There were fifteen of them in all, of whom seven are named,  that is to say, Thorarin, Thorvald the crooked, his son Ketill, Arngrim,  Eystein the Berserker, Thord the son of Rafn, who lived as Stockahlad,  and had married Vigdis, the daughter of Thorir and widow of Sigmund, and  Eyvind, the Norwegian who was staying with Thord. They went to Upsal,  but Thorvard rode to Öngulstad (where there lived a good yeoman, Halli  the fat), and sent his son to Thverà, desiring him to tell Glum the purpose  of the men of Espihole, and afterwards, he added, you will ride back  quickly to meet me.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>When Thorvard came to  Öngulstad, Halli asked what news he had to tell. Nothing as yet, he  replied; but then he told him what was the position of things, and Halli  thought he saw pretty clearly that Thorvard had brought all this trouble  on, and he told him that such men as he were born for mischief, inasmuch  as he desired that every man should be at variance with his neighbour;  and he added, It would serve you right if you were killed. Then Halli  went in a great hurry with all the people, men and women, whom he had  got, with the intention of interfering between the two parties, if it  were necessary. Gudbrand, Thorvards son, got to Thverà, and said that  his father had sent him thither; he told Glum what had occurred, and how  my father thought himself bound to tell you this which concerns you nearly,  that the men of Espihole intend to give notice of outlawry as attaching  to Steinolf. Glums answer was, Why did not your father come himself?  The lad said, I consider it all the same which of us two came. Glum  replied, Your father has done well in sending you hither, if we are in  want of men: so he made him dismount, and fastened up his horse. Gudbrand  exclaimed, My father told me I must get back quickly. Oh, rejoined  Glum, it cannot be so; he was desirous, no doubt, that you should show  your manhood to-day.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>In the meantime Thorvard  began to say, My son Gudbrand is late. Halli inquired whither he had  sent him. I sent him to Thverà, answered Thorvard. It is well, said  Halli, that you should meet with some cunning people, and it serves you  right.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>The men of Espihole rode  across the river with the intention of passing at the Ship-ford. Glum  saw them riding, and remarked that Márr was somewhat too late. Then he  ran out of the homestead with six men, of whom Gudbrand was one, and followed  the other party. He had his shield and a halberd, with his sword by his  side, and hastened on the road, with his men after him, to come up with  them. When Thorarin saw them coming he had his people ride their own way,  no faster and no slower on that account, and no one can blame us for that.  Thord, the son of Rafn, asked Thorarin whether they with twenty men were  to let themselves be chased by Glum with his six? Thorarins answer was,  Let us ride on, for Glums object is to delay us and to wait for his  own people. Thord said, It is no wonder that when he stands on equal  vantage-ground with us we often get the worst of it with Glum; seeing  that now, when he has only a few men with him, you do not dare to wait  for him; but he shall not make me run, and so he dismounted. Eystein  the Berserker said too that he would not ride away from Glum, so that  they should profess to have driven us off. Thorarin observed that this  course seemed to him inexpedient; but when Glum saw that they did not  go on, he slackened his pace, and addressed Thorarin, asking what their  errand was at Upsal. Thorarin replied that they had determined to proclaim  Steinolf as liable to outlawry. Then Glum said, Is not this rather too  strong a measure? Should not some offer of satisfaction be tried first,  and we might possibly hit upon some method for bringing this suit to a  close. Thorarin said that he wanted to delay them and had them ride on,  and so they did. Glum asked them, Will you stay a little bit longer?  but they rode away from him, and as they rode slower, so Glum slackened  his pace and waited for his men, and said, Your cause will not find much  favour, if you rake up a parcel of lies, and it will end only in disgrace.  We shall not look to that now, replied Thorarin; it is a hard matter  to come to terms with you. Whilst they rode on, Glum kept going forward  alongside of them, talking with them, and thus delayed them. But when  he saw he could not keep them back any longer, and felt sure of his own  men coming up, then he threw his spear at Arngrim so that it went through  the mans thigh and the saddle-bow also, and Arngrim was disabled for  the day. Eystein was the first who then rushed at Glum, but Thorvald Tafalld  stood out to meet him, and they two fought with each other. Every other  man thought he was well off in proportion as he kept away from them; for  they were both full of courage and strength, and each of them dealt the  other many and sore strokes. Thorvald the crooked attacked Glum sharply  and many more with him, but Glum and his men got out of their way and  protected themselves as well as they could. Thorarin did not get off his  horse, for he thought that they were quite enough to set on one man.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="23" title="">
   <paragraph>Whilst they  were fighting a man came up at full speed, wearing a hood of skins, with  a sword in his hand. He came where Thorvald Tafalld had fallen before  Eystein, and rushing at the latter, gave him a death-blow. Then he joined  himself to Glums side, and Glum called out to him, Good luck to you  Thundarbenda! I made a good bargain when I bought you. You will pay me  well to-day for the outlay. Now Glum had a thrall who was called by that  name, and that is why he spoke thus; but in reality it was Vigfuss, Glums  son, though few or none except Glum himself knew him, for he had been  three winters outlawed and living in concealment, so that most people  thought he had gone abroad. It happened that whilst Glum was getting away  he fell, and lay on the ground, and his two thralls lay over him, and  were killed with spear-thrusts; but at that moment Márr with his men came  up. Then Thorarin got off his horse, and he and Márr fought, without any  other men meddling with them. Glum sprung up, and joined heartily in the  fight, and there was then no advantage of number on either side. A servant  of Thorarins, named Eirik, who had been about his work in the morning,  came too his maters aid with a club in his hand, but without other arms  of offence of defence; and Glum suffered much by him because his men were  injured both in person and in their arms by that club which he bore. It  is told too that Halldor, Glums wife, called on the women to go with  her, saying, We will bind up the wounds of those men who have any hope  of life, whichever party they belong to. When she came up Thorarin was  just struck down by Márr, his shoulder was cut away in such fashion that  the lungs were exposed. But Halldor bound up his wound, and kept watch  over him till the fight was over.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Halli the fat was the  first who came up to interfere, and may men were with him. The end of  the combat was that five men of those from Espihole were killed, that  is to say, Thorvald the crooked, Arngrim, Eysein, Eirik, and Eyvind the  Norwegian. On Glums side there fell Thorvald Tafalld, Eyiolf son of Thorleif,  Jöd, and the two thralls. Thorarin got home with his people; Glum also  returned with his men, and had the dead carried into an outbuilding, where  the utmost honour was done to the body of Thorvald, for garments were  placed under it, and it was sewn up in a skin. When the men had returned,  Glum said to Halldora, Our expedition to-day would have been successful,  if you had staid at home, and if Thorarin had not escaped with his life.  She replied, There is little of life in Thorarin, and if he lives you  will not be able to remain in the district long; but if he dies you will  not be able to remain in the country at all. After this Glum said to  Gudbrand, You got much honour by your prowess to-day in killing Thorvald  the crooked, and you did us good service. Gudbrand replied that nothing  of the sort had happened; he had only defended himself as well as he could.  Oh, said Glum, that is all very well. I saw clearly what took place;  a mere child in age to kill such a champion as Thorvald! You will always  be talked of for this deed. I got credit abroad in the same way for killing  the Berserker. I never slew Thorvald, answered Gudbrand. It is no  use trying to conceal it, my good friend, you gave him the wound which  killed him. Do not shirk the good luck which has fallen to you. Glum  maintained his point with Gudbrand till the latter believed what he said,  admitted that he had done it, and thought it an honour to himself, so  that it could no longer be concealed, and the death was formally laid  to his charge. This seemed to those who took up the suit for Thorvalds  slaughter to be less promising than had been expected: Thorvald was chosen  as the man whose death was to be avenged.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>People report a speech  of Glums--One thing I do not like, and that is that Márr should have  his head tied up, though he has gat a bump on it. What he called a bump  was in fact a cut crosswise over his head. Márrs answer was, I should  not need this so much if I had lain down and use a couple of thralls as  a shield. Well, my lad, said Glum, our field Hrisateig (Bush acre)  was hard to mow to-day. Márr replied, It will turn out a bad mowing  for you in one way, for you have mowed the land at Thverà out of your  own hands. I do not think you know that for a certainty, rejoined Glum.  I may not know it, but it will turn out for you as if I did now it,  was Márrs answer. Now, when Helga, Glums sister, heard the tidings,  she came over to Thverà and asked how her son had borne himself. There  was no better man, said Glum. I should like to see him dead, said she,  if that is all that is left for me. they allowed her to do so, and she  caused him to be lifted into the waggon, and tenderly handled, and when  she got home she cleansed his wounds and bound them up, and dealt with  him in such a way that he recovered his speech.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>The law was then that  if an equal number of men were killed on either side they were set off  against each other, though there might be a difference in the men themselves;  but if one party had the worst of it they had to select the man for whom  atonement was to be demanded. If anything however, happened to turn up  afterwards, by which it would have seemed better to have made a different  choice, they could not change their selection. When Thorarin heard that  Thorvald Tafalld was alive, he chose his own brother Thorvald the crooked,  as the man to be atoned for. When, however, he found a little afterwards  that the latters death was laid to the charge of Gudbrand, he would gladly  have selected another man, but he had to abide by his first choice. Then  they found Einar the son of Eyiolf, and Thorarin told him he should now  take advantage of that agreement which they had formerly made with each  other. Einar replied, My mind is the same now that it was formerly when  Bárd was killed. he then took up the suit to carry it on at the Thing,  in the summer, and he made the charge against Glum. Thorarin was laid  up with his wounds the whole summer, and so was Thorvald Tafalld, but  they both recovered. Glum had a great number of men with him at the Thing,  and so in fact had both parties. An attempt was now made by persons of  consideration connected with both sides to bring about a settlement of  the case. The suit was compounded on these conditions, that is to say,  that the death of Steinolf was to be considered as atoned for, if Vigfuss,  Glums son, were proclaimed free from his penalty. Gudbrand, however,  was convicted of the death of Thorvald, and Glum got him taken abroad.  They returned home with affairs in this condition; but Thorvard and Thorarin  were very much dissatisfied, and the latter thought he had obtained no  honourable satisfaction for the death of his brother Thorvald. Glum remained  at home much looked up to, and in the course of the winter there got abroad  a stanza which he had lately composed:</paragraph>
   <poetry>
    <line>She asks--he nymph that pours the wine--</line>
    <line>the deeds of death that I have done.</line>
    <line>Theyre past and gone, those deeds of mine;</line>
    <line>But no man yet has talked of one.</line>
   </poetry>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="24" title="">
   <paragraph>One day,  when men had got together at the warm bath of Hrafnagil, Thorvard came  thither. He was a merry fellow, and amused himself in many ways. What  men, he asked, have you got here who can entertain us with some fresh  stories? There is plenty of amusement and fun where you are, they said.  Well, he replied, nothing amuses me more than reciting Glums verses;  but I keep thinking over what can be the faulty reckoning he speaks of  in one of his stanzas, when he says he did not get credit for all the  people he had killed. What are we to suppose to be the real state of the  case? Which is more likely, that Gudbrand killed Thorvald, or that Glum  did it? This view seemed to many men worth consideration, and Thorvard  rode to meet Thorarin, and said to him, I have been thinking the matter  out, and I am convinced that the truth has not been known about the death  of Thorvald the crooked. You will find in Glums verses, that he says  he has not got credit for all the men he has killed. Thorarin answered,  I can hardly take the case up again, though you should be right, and  so things shall remain as they are. Thorvard rejoined, That is not a  proper course, although if the matter had not been revived, all might  have gone on quietly; no I shall talk of it publicly, and there will fall  on you disgrace greater than any which has yet ensued in this affair.  Well, said Thorarin, it seems to me an awkward matter to carry this  cause to the Althing, in the face of the power of Glum and his kinsmen.  Thorvard replied, I can give you a piece of advice on that point. Summon  him to the Hegranes Thing: you have plenty of kinsmen there, and he will  find it hard to defend the case. That we will do, said Thorarin, an  so they parted.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>The spring was a bad one,  and everything became difficult to procure. At that time Thorarin set  on foot the suit as against Glum at Hegranes Thing, inasmuch as all the  priests of the different division in the district who belonged to that  Thing, were bound to Thorarin by the ties of kindred. It was scarcely  possible to get across the moors with horses, on account of the snow.  So Glum adopted the plan of putting a large vessel into the charge of  his brother, Thorstein, who was to sail in her to the westward, and convey  arms and provisions to the Thing. When, however, they came off Ulfsdal,  the ship went to pieces, and all the men and property on board her were  lost. Glum got to the Thing with a hundred and twenty men, but he could  not encamp nearer to the place itself than in the outer circle, or verge  of the court.  Einar,  the son of Eyiolf, with the men of Espihole, was already there. Word was  sent to Glum that he was to present himself to the court, and produce  his plea in answer to the indictment. Glum went accordingly, but the men  were drawn up on both sides in such a way that there was not more space  than would allow of one man passing, and Glum was desired to go into the  enclosure if he wanted to get to the court. He did not think this an advisable  course, so he said to his men, It is easy to see that they think they  have got our affair in their own hands now. Well, it may be so, but I  should like you to fall back and change your order. I will march first,  then two men following me in a line, and then four in a line after them,  and so on; and we will march right at them, keeping our spears before  us, and this sort of wedge must make its way in if you follow close up.  They did this, and pushed without interruption right into the ring which  was cleared for the court, but it was night long before they could be  got of the ground again, so as to allow the court to sit; so great was  the crush and press. At last it was brought about that the court was reconstituted,  and they were proceeding to sum up the case when Glum came forward on  the bank were the court was held, and called his witnesses to the fact  that the sun had risen again on the field of the Thing; then he protested  solemnly against any judgment being given in the case before them. It  followed from this protest that every suit before the court at once discontinued  and fell to the ground. Men rode away, and the people of Espihole were  very ill pleased with what had happened.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Thorarin declared that  Glum had dealt vexatiously with them, but Einar replied, The matter does  not appear to me to be so very ugly, for the suit may be taken up again  at the point where it left off. Afterwards the men of Espihole rode to  the Althing with Einar, and with many of their friends who had promised  them their support against glum. Glums kinsmen gave him their help also  in securing the benefit of the point of law, and the matter was settled  by the advice of skilled men, on condition that Glum would take an oath  in the case to the effect that he did not kill Thorvald the crooked. So  when many men interceded, they compounded the matter on these terms--that  Glum should swear he had not slain him; and the time was appointed when  the oath should be taken, that is to say, in the autumn, five weeks before  winter. They followed up the suit with such vigour that they were determined  to bring it on again, if he did not take the necessary oath in three temples  on the Eyjafirth, and if it were not done at the prescribed time the right  to clear himself by the oath was to be forfeited. There was much talk  about this business, and what Gums oaths would be, and how he would get  on with them.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="25" title="">
   <paragraph>Now men  returned from the Thing, and Glum staid at home all the summer: everything  was quiet in the district till it came to the time of the Leet,  when they assembled at that court. Glum,  however, was not there, and nothing was heard of him. Márr was at home  in his dwelling; but in the autumn, five weeks before winter, he held  a wedding-feast, and invited men to it, so that not less than a hundred  and twenty people came together. This invitation appeared strange to everybody,  for those who were concerned in the wedding were not persons of any consequence.  That evening all the men of Eyjafirth were seen riding in from the dales  two or five at a time, and the people who came down into the district  were all collected in one body. Glum was there, and Asgrim, and Gizor,  with three hundred and sixty men, and they came in the course of the night  to the homestead, and sat at the wedding-feast.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>The morning after Glum  sent to find Thorarin, and told him to come to Diupadal, not later than  six in the morning, to hear the oaths. Thorarin bestirred himself and  got together a hundred and twenty men, and when they came to the temple,  six people went into it, that is to say, Gizor and Asgrim with Glum, and  Einar and Hlenni the old with Thorarin. Whoever had to take the temple  oath laid hold with his hand of the silver ring, which was stained red  with the blood of the cattle sacrificed, and which ought not to weigh  less than three ounces. Then Glum said word for word thus: I name Asgrim  to bear witness, and Gizor in the second place to bear witness, that I  take the temple oath, on the ring, and I say it to the God.  When Thorvald the crooked got his death-blow--</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Vark at þar--ok vák ek þar--ok raudk at þ odd ok egg. </paragraph>
   <paragraph>Now let those men who are skilled in such matters, and who stand by, look to my oath.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Thorarin and his friends were not prepared  to find any fault, but they said they had never heard the form of words  used before. In the same manner the oaths were taken by Glum at Gnupafell  and at Thverà. Gizor and Asgrim stayed some nights at Thverà, and when  they went away Glum gave Gizor the blue cloak, and he gave Asgrim the  gold-mounted spear (which Vigfuss had given him).</paragraph>
   <paragraph>In the course of the winter Thorvard met Thorarin, and asked him, Did Glum  take the oath properly? We found nothing to take hold of, said Thorarin.  It is a wonderful thing, replied Thorvard, that wise people should  make such mistakes. I have known men who have declared themselves to have  slain others, but I have never known a case of a man swearing explicitly  that he was guilty, as Glum did. How could he say more than he did when  he declared that he was there at the doing of the deed, that he took  part in the death, and that he reddened point and edge, when Thorvald  the crooked fell at Hrisateig?--though I admit that he did not pronounce  the words as they are commonly pronounced. That scandal will never be  done away with. Thorarin replied, I did not observe this, but I am tired  of having to do with Glum. Well, said Thorvard, if you are tired because  your health is not equal to it, let Einar take the matter up. He is a  prudent man, with a great kindred, and many will follow him. His brother  Gudmund will not be neutral, and he himself is most anxious for one thing-to  get to Thverà. Then they met Einar and consulted with him, and Thorarin  said, If you will take the lead in the suit many men will back you in  it, and we will bring it about that you shall have Glums land, at a price  not exceeding that which he paid to Thorkel the tall. Einar observed,  Glum has now parted with those two things, his cloak and his spear, which  his mothers father, Vigfuss, gave him, and bad him keep, if he wished  to hold his position, telling him that he would fall away in dignity from  the time that he let them out of his hands. Now will I take up the suit  and follow it out.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="26" title="">
   <paragraph>Einar now  set the suit on foot afresh for the Althing, and both sides collected  their people together, but before Glum left home he dreamt that many persons  came to Thverà to visit the god Frey, and he thought he saw a great crowd  on the sand-banks by the river, with Frey sitting on a chair. He dreamt  that he asked who they were who had come thither, and they said, We are  thy departed kindred, and we are now begging Frey that thou mayst not  be driven out of Thverà, but it is no use, for he answers shortly and  angrily, and calls to mind now the gift of the ox by Thorkel the tall.  At that point Glum woke up, and ever afterwards he professed that he was  on worse terms with Frey.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Men rode to the Thing,  and the suit was brought to a close in such a way that Glum admitted the  killing of Thorvald; but his kinsmen and friends exerted themselves to  secure the acceptance of a settlement rather than the imposition of outlawry  or banishment. So they compounded the matter at the Thing, on the condition  that Glum was to forfeit the land at Thverà, half absolutely as an atonement  to Ketell, the son of Thorvald the crooked, and to convey the other half  at a valuation; but he was allowed to live there till the spring, and  was then to be outlawed in the district, and not to live nearer than in  Hörgardal. So they left the Thing. Einar afterwards bought the land, as  had been promised to him. In the spring his men came thither to work on  the farm, and Einar told them that they should give an account to him  of every word which Glum spoke. One day he came and talked with them on  this wise, It is easy to see that Einar has got good workmen about him;  the work is well done on the land, and it is now of consequence that great  and little matters should both be attended to. You would do well to put  up posts here by the water side for drying clothes; it is convenient for  the women washing the larger articles; the wells at home are indifferent.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>When they got home Einar  asked what Glum had said to them. They told him how careful he was with  reference to all the work done. Did it appear to you, said he, that  he was desirous of getting everything ready for my hands? Yes, they  replied, so we think. Well, replied Einar, I think differently. I  think he meant very likely to hang you on these posts, or stick on them  some insult to me. You must not go there, however.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Einar transferred his  household to Thverà in the spring, but Glum remained where he was till  the last day for moving,  and when people were all ready to start he sat down on the high seat and  did not move, although he was summoned to do so. He had the hall decorated  with hangings, and refused to turn out like mere cottage tenants. Hallbera,  the daughter of Thorodd, the son of Hialm, was the mother of Gudmund and  Einar, and lived at Hanakamb. She came to Thverà, and saluted Glum, saying,  Good morning to you, Glum, but you cannot stay here any longer. I have  marked out the land of Thverà with fire, and I eject you and all yours  formally from it, as made over to my son Einar.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Then Glum rose up and told her she might chatter away like a miserable  old woman as she was; but as he rode away he looked over his shoulder  towards the homestead and sung a stanza--</paragraph>
   <poetry>
    <line>With sword and spear, as fame hath told,</line>
    <line>Like many a gallant earl of old,</line>
    <line>I won these lands by might and main.</line>
    <line>But now the wielder of the brand</line>
    <line>Has dashd at last from out his hand,</line>
    <line>Broad lands and lordships lost again.</line>
   </poetry>
   <paragraph>Glum lived at Mödrufell, in Hörgardal, with Thorgrim  Fiuk, but he was not content to remain there more than one winter. Then  he dwelt two winters in Myrkárdal, but a landslip fell near the homestead  and destroyed some of the buildings. After that he bought land at Thverbrek,  in Öxnadal, and dwelt there as long as he lived, and became aged and blind.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="27" title="">
   <paragraph>There was  a man named Narvi who dwelt at Hrisey. He had as his wife Ulfeida, the  daughter of Ingiald, son of Helgi the thin. Their sons were Eyiolf, Klængr,  Thorbrand, and Thorvald, all distinguished men and kinsmen of Glums.  Two of these, Klæengr and Eyiolf, lived at Hrisey, after their fathers  death. A man named Thorvald, who had married Helga, the daughter of Thord,  the son of Hraf, of Stöckahlad, and who was nicknamed Menni, dwelt at  Hagi at that time. One spring Thorvald came from Hagi, and lay off Hrisey  in his vessel, intending to fish, and when Klængr was aware of this he  stared with him. They got out into the firth, and fell in with a whale  which was just dead, which they made fast and towed into the firth in  the course of the day. Klængr wanted to bring the carcass into Hrisey,  because the distance was shorter, but Thorvald desired to tow it to Hagi,  and said he had and equal right to do so. Klængr maintained that it was  not the law to take it anywhere except to the nearest point where any  of the men engaged in the capture owned land. Thorvald asserted his rights,  and said that Glums kinsmen had no business to interfere with the fair  partition of the fish. Whatever the laws were, the strongest should now  have their way. At that moment Thorvald had the largest number of men  with him, and so they took the drift fish from Klængr by force, though  both of them were land-owners. Klængr went home very much dissatisfied,  and Thorvald and his people laughed at him and his party, telling them  they did not dare to hold on to their booty.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>One morning Klængr got  up early, and went with three other men in to Hagi, so as to be there  in good time whilst people were still asleep. Then Klængr said--Well  try a scheme; here are cattle about in the homestead; we will drive them  on to the buildings, under which Thorvald is asleep, and so we shall get  him to come out. They  did this, and Thorvald woke up and rushed out of doors. Klængr made at  him, and gave him a mortal wound; but went away again without daring to  declare himself the slayer, because there were so many people about on  the spot. So he went out to one of the islands, and there declared that  he had killed Thorvald. The right of claiming atonement belonged to Thorarin  and Thord, and they treated the case as one of murder. When the suit was being brought before  the Thing, Glum was quiet at home, but whilst the Thing was going on he  went about in the districts of Fliot and Svarvadardal, begging for help  to meet the execution of the anticipated sentence of forfeiture; however,  he asked men to say nothing of this intention of his. Klaufi, of Bárd,  exclaimed, To be sure we will help Glum; he married Halldora, the daughter  of Arnor Red-cheek; and many men besides promised to support him. Then  Glum returned home, but the suit ran its course at the Thing, and when  that was over they got ready to carry out the sentence of forfeiture with  four ships, and thirty men in each ship. Einar, Thorarn, and Thord commanded  the ships, and when they came in-shore at the island, in the twilight  of morning, they saw a smoke rising over the buildings. Einar asked his  people whether it appeared to them, as it did to him, that the smoke was  not a clear blue. They answered that so it seemed to them. Then, said  Einar, it appears likely to me from that smoke that there are a good  many people in the house, and that steam hanging in the air must be the  steam from men. If this be so we shall find out about it by rowing away  from the island openly and then we shall be sure if there by any number  of men there. They did this, and when the men who were in the island  saw them they rushed out to their vessels, and put out after them, for  Glum had come thither with two hundred and forty men, and they chased  them right up to Oddaeyr, so that the sentence of forfeiture was not carried  out, and the men of Eyjafirth got dishonour by the failure.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>Glum remained in his own  dwelling through the summer. He had to open an Autumn court; but the place  of holding it is on the east of the firth, not far from Kaupáng, and the  men of Eyjafirth got a large force together, whilst Glum had only thirty  men. Many people spoke to Glum and told him that he ought not to go with  a small number of followers. His answer was, The finest portion of my  life is gone by, and I am pleased that they have not driven me so hard  that I cannot ride the straight path. He went up the firth in a ship,  and then disembarked and went to he booths. Now between the firth and  the booths there are certain steep ascents covered with loose gravel,  and when Glum came opposite to the booth which belonged to Einar, men  rushed out upon him and his people and dashed their shields against them  so as to push them down the slope. Glum fell and rolled shield and all  down the bank on to the spit of sand below. He was not wounded, but three  spears had stuck in his shield. Thorvald Tafalld had then come to shore  and saw that Glum was in a strait: he jumped on land with his oar in his  hand and, running up the slope, hurled it at Gudmund the powerful: it  came against his shield, which broke, and the handle of the oar struck  him on the breast so that he fell down senseless and was carried off by  four men to his booth. Then they challenged one another to come on, and  cast weapons and stones on both sides, and the contest was a hard one;  many were wounded; but all said the same thing--that it was impossible  for a small number to fight better than Glum and his men had done. Einar  and his men made a vigorous onslaught; but people interfered, and it ended  in Glum losing two men, Klængr, the son of Narvi, and Grim Eyrarlegg,  the brother of his wife Halldora. Then Brusi, the son of Halli, made these  verses:</paragraph>
   <poetry>
    <line>Thou warrior-goddess of the shield!</line>
    <line>We held our own in battle fray--</line>
    <line>I know tis so--we did not yield</line>
    <line>The honour of the day.</line>
   </poetry>
   <poetry>
    <line>Those chiefs forsooth, the while we fought,</line>
    <line>(Bright nymph! it may not be denied)</line>
    <line>Strode somewhat faster than I though</line>
    <line>Adown the steep hill side.</line>
   </poetry>
   <paragraph>Then Einar composed a stanza:</paragraph>
   <poetry>
    <line>he had to run away perforce</line>
    <line>From out the fight--that swordsman bold--</line>
    <line>I trow twas hard to stop his course</line>
    <line>As down the bank he rolld.</line>
   </poetry>
   <poetry>
    <line>Well usd the pirates spear to wield,</line>
    <line>In vain that chieftain fought,</line>
    <line>And the loose shingle faild to yield</line>
    <line>The foothold which he sought.</line>
   </poetry>
   <paragraph>Then Glum composed some verses in answer to him:</paragraph>
   <poetry>
    <line>Though standing on the band so high</line>
    <line>Their helmets made a gallant show,</line>
    <line>They did not dare their luck to try</line>
    <line>Upon the beach below.</line>
   </poetry>
   <poetry>
    <line>They did not dare to risk the path,</line>
    <line>Whilst on the sandy shore we stood,</line>
    <line>And fac'd the dread Valkyries wrath</line>
    <line>With shields that drippd with blood.</line>
   </poetry>
   <paragraph>The matter was settled upon  the ground that the death of Klængr and Thorvald of Hagi were set off  one against the other, and the slaying of Grim Eyrarlegg was considered  equal to the injury caused to Gudmund; but Glum was much dissatisfied  with this close of the suit, as he expressed himself in the following  stanza, which he made afterwards:</paragraph>
   <poetry>
    <line>The world is worthless; and my life</line>
    <line>With all the keen delights of strife</line>
    <line>Hath well-nigh passed away.</line>
    <line>Too weak, when gallant Grim lay low,</line>
    <line>To strike mid men th'avenging blow,</line>
    <line>And blood with blood repay!</line>
   </poetry>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="28" title="">
   <paragraph>It happened one summer that the brothers Gudmund and Einar were riding  back from the Thing, when Glum invited some guests to his house, and he sent  men up to Öxnadal-heath and asked those brothers also, professing that he  wished to be reconciled to them wholly and entirely. For, said he, on account  of old age I am fit for nothing, and I will not invite them only to a  meal. Glum was then blind, but he caused a look-out to be kept for their  coming. Gudmund wished to accept the invitation, but Einar did not; and  each of them rode on his own side of the river, till Glum was told that  one of the two troops was coming that way. Then, said he, Einar will  not accept the invitation; he is so distrustful that he will put confidence  in no man. It is reported that Einar called out to Gudmund and said,  If you go thither this evening, I will be sure to be there tomorrow;  but Gudmund reflected on those words and said, Well, you must mean that  you will have to take measures for avenging my death; and so he turned  round and followed Einar. It was told to Glum that neither of the two  was coming. Then it is a bad business, exclaimed he, for if I had gone  to meet them, I had made up my mind not to miss both of them. He had  a drawn sword under his cloak. So this was the last thing which passed  between Glum and the men of Eyjafirth.</paragraph>
   <paragraph>When Christianity was  introduced in these parts Glum was baptized, and lived three winters afterwards.  He was confirmed in his last illness by Bishop Kol, and died in white  vestments. Márr, Glums son, lived at Forn-Hagi, and caused a church to  be built there, in which Glum and Márr himself, when he died, were buried.  Many other people also were buried there, because for a long time there  was but that one church in Hörgárdal. People relate that for twenty years  Glum was the greatest chief on Eyjafirth; and for another twenty years  there were no greater men there, though some were on an equal footing  with him. They say too that of all the valiant men that have been in this  land he had the noblest spirit. And so ends the Story of Glum.</paragraph>
  </chapter>
 </content>
</document>
